主演: 汤姆·汉克斯
片名: 阿甘正传
你好  我叫福雷斯  福雷斯·甘
Hello. My name's Forrest Forrest Gump.
要吃巧克力吗?
Do you want a chocolate?
我能吃掉上百万块巧克力
I could eat about a million and a half of these.
我妈妈常说
My mama always said
人生就像一盒各式各样的巧克力
Life was like a box of chocolates.
你永远不知道下一块将会是哪种
You never know what you're going to get.
那双鞋子一定很舒适
Those must be comfortable shoes.
穿这样的鞋子你可以走上一整天
I bet you could walk all day in shoes like that
脚都不会痛
and not feel a thing.
我希望能有一双这样的鞋子
I wish I had shoes like that.
其实我的脚很痛
My feet hurt.
妈妈常说要想知道一个人的很多事情
Mama always said there's an awful lot
只要看看他穿的鞋就能知道
you can tell about a person by their shoes.
他会往哪里走
Where they're going,
他住在哪里
where they've been.
我穿过很多双鞋子
I've worn lots of shoes.
如果我仔细想的话
I bet if I think about it real hard
我能记得我第一双鞋子的模样
I could remember my first pair of shoes.
妈妈说它会带我到任何地方
Mama said they'd take me anywhere.
她说它是双魔鞋
She said they was my magic shoes.
好的  福雷斯  张开双眼
All right, Forrest, Open your eyes now.
你走几步看看
Let's take a little walk around.
感觉如何?
How do those feel?
他的双腿很强壮  甘太太
His legs are strong, Mrs. Gump,
是我见过最强壮的
as strong as I've ever seen.
但是他的背象政客一样弯
But his back's as crooked as a politician.
但我们会让他再直起来  对吧?
But we're going to straighten him right up, aren't we, Forrest?
福雷斯!
Forrest!
我刚出世时
Now, when I was a baby,
妈妈用了一位内战英雄的名字为我取名
Mama named me after the great Civil War hero
内森贝·弗福雷斯将军
General Nathan Bedford Forrest.
她说我们有点亲戚关系
She said we was related to him in some way.
他做过的事情是：
What he did was,
建立了一个俱乐部叫三Ｋ党
he tarted up this club called the Ku Klux Klan.
他们全披着长袍和床单
They'd all dress up in their robes and their bed sheets
看来像一群鬼
and act like a bunch of ghosts or spooks or something.
他们还在马上也披了床单四处跑
They'd even put bed sheets on their horses and ride around.
不管怎样  这就是我名字的由来：福雷斯·甘
And, anyway, that'show I got my name... Forrest Gump.
妈妈说这名字是提醒我
Mama said the Forrest part was to remind me
我们会经常做一些
that sometimes we all do things that, well,
并没有意义的事情
that just don't make no sense.
好了
All right.
你们在看什么?
What are y'all staring at?
从来没有见过
Haven't you ever seen
小孩子戴脚撑的吗?
a little boy with braces on his legs before?
不要管其它人
Don't ever let anybody
说他们比你强  福雷斯
tell you they're better than you, Forrest.
如果上帝要让人人都一样的话
If God intended everybody to be the same,
他会给每人一双脚撑
he'd have given us all braces on our legs.
妈妈总有办法让我明白她的意思
Mama always had a way of explaining things so I could understand them.
我们住在17号公路附近
We lived about a quarter mile off Route 17,
距离亚拉巴马州绿茵镇约半哩
about a half mile from the town of Greenbow, Alabama.
这个地方属于绿茵县
That's in the county of Greenbow.
我们的房子来自妈妈的家族
Our house had been in Mama's family
从她爷爷的爷爷的爷爷传下来的
since her grandpa's grandpa's grandpa
他大概在一千年前飘洋过海来这里
had come across the ocean about a thousand years ago.
房子只有我和妈妈住
Since it was just me and Mama
我们有好多空房间
and we had all these empty rooms,
妈妈将这些空房出租
Mama decided to let those rooms out,
给路过的人住
mostly to people passing through,
比如从莫比镇、或蒙哥马利镇来的人
Like from, oh, Mobile, Montgomery, places like that.
我和妈妈靠这个挣到钱
That's how me and Mama got money.
妈妈是个很聪明的女士
Mama was a real smart lady.
记住我说的话,福雷斯
Remember what I told you, Forrest.
你和其它任何人是一样的
You're no different than anybody else is.
听清楚了没有  福雷斯?
Did you hear what I said, Forrest?
你和其它人是一样的
You're the same as everybody else.
你并没有什么不一样
You are no different.
你的孩子有点不一样  甘太太
Your boy's... different, Mrs. Gump.
他的智商只有75
His I. Q is 75.
我们都是不一样的
Well, we're all different,
汉考克先生
Mr. Hancock.
她希望我得到最好的教育
She wanted me to have the finest education
所以她带我去绿茵县中心学校
so she to ok me to the Greenbow County Central School.
我见到了校长什么的
I met the principal and all.
请你看看这个  甘太太
I want to show you something, Mrs. Gump.
这是正常水平
Now, this is normal.
福雷斯则是在这儿
Forrest is right here.
州政府要求智商起码要80
The state require s a minimum I. Q of 80
才能上公立学校
to attend public school.
甘太太
Mrs. Gump,
他应该上特殊学校
he's going to have to go to a special school.
在那里他会很好的
Now, he'll be just fine.
正常水平是什么意思?
What does normal mean anyway?
他可能...
He might be...
反应不太灵敏
a bit on the slow side,
但我儿子福雷斯
but my boy Forrest
应该和其它人一样得到机会
is going to get the same opportunities as everyone else.
他不该去特殊学校
He's not going to some special school
学怎么翻修轮胎
to learn how to retread tires.
这不过是区区5分的问题
We're talking about five little points here.
一定会有办法解决的
There must be something can be done.
我们的学校是要排名次的
We're a progressive school system.
我们不想有人拉后腿
We don't want to see anybody left behind.
甘先生在哪儿  甘太太?
Is there a Mr. Gump, Mrs. Gump?
他去度假了
He's on vacation.
你妈妈真是很关心你的教育  孩子
Well, your mama sure does care about your schooling, son.
你不太会说话  是吗?
You don't say much, do you?
最后  他必须去试一试
Finally, he had to try.
看起来容易  但是...
It looked easy, but...
发生了怪事  首先他们...
oh, what happened. First they...
妈妈  度假是什么意思?
Mama, what's vacation mean?
度假?
Vacation?
爸爸去哪儿了?
Where Daddy went?
度假就是你去一个地方...
Vacation's when you go somewhere...
然后就不再回来
and you don't ever come back.
总之  我想你可以说
Anyway, I guess you could say
我和妈妈无依无靠
me and Mama was on our own.
但我们不介意
But we didn't mind.
我们的房子总住满了人
Our house was never empty.
经常是人来人往的
There was always folks coming and going.
开饭了!
Supper!
大家来吃晚饭啦!
It's supper, everyone!
这看起来很特别
That sure looks special.
有时有这么多人和我们一起住
Sometimes, we had so many people staying with us
每个房间都住满了旅客
that every room was filled, with travelers, you know,
这些人带着行李箱子
folks living out of their suitcases
还有帽子箱子  还有样品箱子
and hat cases and sample cases.
福雷斯·甘  吃晚饭了!  福雷斯?
Forrest Gump, it's suppertime! Forrest?
有一次  又有位年青人和我们住一起
One time, a young man was staying with us,
他带着一个吉它箱子
and he had him a guitar case.
你从来逮不到兔子
Well, you ain't never caught a rabbit
你也不是...
And you ain't no
我的朋友
Friend of mine
福雷斯
Forrest,
叫你不要打扰这位叔叔
I told you not to bother this nice young man.
不  没关系  太太
No, that's all right, ma'am.
我在弹吉它给他听
I was showing him a thing or two on the guitar.
好吧  你可以来吃晚饭了
All right. Supper's ready if y'all want to eat.
行  好极了  谢谢你  太太
Yeah, that sounds good. Thank you, ma'am.
喂  兄弟  请你再表演一遍刚才那步法
Say, man, show me that crazy little walk you did there.
稍微慢一点
Slow it down some.
你只不过是...
You ain't nothing but...
我喜欢那吉它
I liked that guitar.
它很好听
It sounded good.
我伴着音乐移动着脚步
I started moving around to the music,
扭着我的臀部
swinging my hips.
哭喊不停
Cryin' all the time
那天晚上
This one night,
我和妈妈出去购物
me and Mama was out shopping,
我们路过文斯家私商店
and we walked by Vincy's Furniture and Appliance Store,
你猜怎么着?
and guess what?
你只不过是一条猎犬
You ain't nothin' but a hound dog
哭喊不停
Cryin' all the time
你只不过是一条猎犬
You ain't nothin' but a hound dog
小孩子不能看这个
This is not for children's eyes.
哭喊不停
Cryin' all the time
几年以后
Some years later,
听说那位帅哥被人称为"猫王"
that handsome young man who they called the King,
嗯  他唱的歌实在太多
well, he sung too many songs.
结果他得了心脏病什么的
Had him self a heart attack or something.
看来"王"确实是不好当啊
It must be hard being a king.
你知道  你的记忆有时清楚得不得了
You know, it's funny how you remember some things,
有时却什么也不记得
but some things you can't.
你要开始努力学习了  福雷斯
You do your very best now, Forrest.
我一定会的  妈妈
I sure will, Mama.
我记得第一次乘校车去上学
I remember the bus ride on the first day of school
非常清楚
very well.
你上不上车?
Are you coming along?
妈妈说不要上陌生人的车子
Mama said not to be taking rides from strangers.
这是校车
This is the bus to school.
我是福雷斯...  福雷斯·甘
I'm Forrest... Forrest Gump.
我是多萝西·哈里斯
I'm Dorothy Harris.
嗯  现在我们不是陌生人了
Well, now we ain't strangers anymore.
这位子有人了
This seat's taken.
有人了
It's taken.
你不准坐这儿
You can't sit here.
你知道  孩子记事实在奇怪
You know, it's funny what a young man recollects,
我不记得我的出生
Because I don 't remember being born.
我不记得我的第一份圣诞礼物
I don't recall what I got for my first Christmas,
我也不记得
and I don't know
我第一次去野餐
when I went on my first outdoor picnic,
但我却记得
but I do remember
我第一次听到最甜的声音
the first time I heard the sweetest voice
在整个世界上
in the wide world.
你愿意的话可以坐这儿
You can sit here if you want.
我一生再没见过如此美丽的人
I had never seen anything so beautiful in my life.
她就象一位天使
She was like an angel.
你想坐还是不想坐?
Well, are you going to sit down or aren't you?
你的腿怎么啦?
What's wrong with your legs?
没什么  谢谢你
Um, nothing at all, thank you.
我的的腿好得很
My legs are just fine and dandy.
我和她在并排坐在校车里
I just sat next to her on that bus
去学校途中我们一直在说话
and had a conversation all the way to school.
当时我的背象个问号那么弯
My back's crooked like a question mark.
除了妈妈  没有人和我说话
Next to Mama, no one ever talked to me
或问我问题
or asked me questions.
你是不是有点傻?
Are you stupid or something?
妈妈说  "做傻事的才是傻瓜"
Mama says, "Stupid is as stupid does."
我叫珍妮
I'm Jenny.
我叫福雷斯...  福雷斯·甘
I'm Forrest... Forrest Gump.
由那天开始  我们经常在一起
From that day on, we was always together.
珍妮和我形影不离
Jenny and me was like peas and carrots.
她教我怎么爬树
She taught me how to climb.
快  福雷斯  你能做到
Move, Forrest, you can do it.
我教她怎么摇摆
I showed her how to dangle.
"一个好小..."
"A good little..."
她帮我学怎么认字
She helped me learn how to read,
我教她怎么倒挂
and I showed her how to swing.
有时  我们就那么坐着
Sometimes, we'd just sitout
等星星出来
and wait for the stars.
妈妈会担心我的
Mama's going to worry about me.
再呆一会儿
Just stay a little longer.
不知为什么  珍妮从来不爱回家
For some reason, Jenny didn 't never want to go home.
好吧  珍妮  我再呆一会儿
Ok, Jenny, I'll stay.
她是我最好的朋友
She was my most special friend.
我唯一的朋友
My only friend.
妈妈总是对我说
Now, my mama always told me
每天都会有奇迹
that miracles happen every day
有些人并不同意
Some people don't think so,
但这是真的
but they do.
嗨  傻瓜!
Hey, dummy!
你是哑巴  还是真的是傻瓜?
Are you dumb, or just plain stupid?
喂  我是福雷斯·甘
Look, I'm Forrest Gimp.
快跑  福雷斯
Just run away, Forrest.
跑  福雷斯!
Run, Forrest!
快跑!  快!
Run away! Hurry!
骑上自行车!
Get the bikes!
我们去捉他!  快点!
Let's get him! Come on!
小心点  阿甘!
Look out, Gump!
我们来捉你了!
We're going to get you!
跑  福雷斯  跑!
Run, Forrest, run!
跑  福雷斯!
Run, Forrest!
你给我回来!
Come back here, you!
跑  福雷斯!
Run, Forrest!
跑!
Run!
你现在大概不会相信我的话...
Now, you wouldn't believe if I told you...
但我跑起来像风一样
but I could run like the wind blows.
从那天开始
From that day on,
如果我要去哪里
if I was going somewhere,
我就跑着去
I was running.
那孩子真是个能跑的傻瓜
That boy sure is a running fool.
记不记得我告诉过你
Now, remember how I told you
珍妮总是不爱回家?
that Jenny never seemed to want to go home?
她家的房子和亚拉巴马州一样老
She lived in a house that was as old as Alabama.
她五岁时她妈妈就去天堂了
Her mama had gone to heaven when she was 5,
她的爸爸好象是个农夫
and her daddy was some kind of a farmer.
珍妮?
Jenny?
他是个非常有爱心的人
He was a very loving man.
他经常亲吻抚摸她和她姐妹
He was always kissing and touching her and her sisters.
后来有一次
And then this one time,
珍妮没有来乘车去学校
Jenny wasn't on the bus to go to school.
珍妮  你今天怎么不来学校?
Jenny, why didn't you come to school today?
嘘  爸爸正在午睡
Shh. Daddy's taking a nap.
珍妮!
Jenny!
快点!
Come on!
珍妮  你往哪儿跑?
Jenny, where'd you run to?
你最好马上回来  丫头!
You better get back here, girl!
你在哪儿?
Where you at?
珍妮!
Jenny!
珍妮  你在哪儿?
Jenny, where you at?
珍妮!
Jenny!
和我一起祈祷  福雷斯
Pray with me, Forrest.
和我一起祈祷
Pray with me.
珍妮!
Jenny!
亲爱的上帝  把我变成一只会飞的鸟吧
Dear God, make me a bird so I can fly far,
飞得越远越好
far, far away from here.
亲爱的上帝  把我变成一只会飞的鸟吧
Dear God, make me a bird so I can fly far.
妈妈常说上帝是神秘的
Mama always said God is mysterious.
珍妮!
Jenny!
那天他没有把珍妮变成一只鸟
He didn 't turn Jenny in to a bird that day.
而是...
Instead...
他叫来了警察
he had the police say
说珍妮再也不必住在那间房子里了
Jenny didn't have to stay in that house no more.
后来她和她祖母住在一起
She was to live with her grandma,
就是克里克大街那里
just over on Creekmore Avenue,
我很高兴  因为她那里离我家很近
which made me happy, 'cause she was so close.
有时晚上
Some nights,
珍妮会溜出来
Jenny'd sneak out
跑到我的房子里
and come on over to my house,
因为她说她很害怕
just'cause she said she was scared.
害怕什么  我不知道
Scared of what, I don 't know.
我猜是怕她祖母的狗
But I think it was her grandma's dog.
他是只很凶的狗
He was a mean dog.
总之  珍妮和我是最好的朋友
Anyway, Jenny and me was best friends
一直到上中学
all the way up through high school.
嗨  傻瓜!
Hey, stupid!
住手!
Quit it!
跑  福雷斯  跑!
Run, Forrest, run!
你没听见吗  傻瓜?
didn't you hear me, stupid?
跑  福雷斯!
Run, Forrest!
快上卡车!
Get in the truck!
快!  他要跑了!  快追!
Come on! He's getting away! Move it!
跑  福雷斯!  跑!
Run, Forrest! Run!
快追  快追!
Move it! Move it!
你快跑吧!
You better be runnin'!
哇!  快!
Whoo-hoo! Go!
跑  福雷斯!
Run, Forrest!
一直以来
Now, it used to be
我到哪儿都跑着去
I ran to get where I was going.
我没想过后来会跑遍所有地方
I never thought it would take me anywhere.
那究竟是什么人?
Who in the hell is that?
那人叫福雷斯·甘  教练
That there is Forrest Gump, Coach.
当地的傻瓜
Just a local idiot.
你能相信吗?
And can you believe it?
我也能上大学了
I got to go to college, too.
福雷斯  快!
Forrest, move it!
跑!
Run!
好!
O.K.!
跑!
Run!
跑  你这狗娘养的傻瓜!  跑!
Run, you stupid son of a bitch! Run!
跑  狗娘养的  跑!  快跑!
Run, son of a bitch, run! Go! Run!
跑!  跑!
Run! Run! Go!
他大概是狗娘养的最傻的傻瓜
He must be the stupidest son of a bitch alive,
但他跑得真是快
but he sure is fast.
也许只是我这样觉得
Now, maybe it's just me,
但大学生活让我非常迷惑
but college was very confusing times.
联邦军队  执行法庭的判决
Federal troops, enforcing a court order,
今天在亚拉巴马大学取缔种族隔离
integrated the University of Alabama today.
允许两名黑人进学校
Two Negroes were admitted,
但乔治华莱士州长随后
but only after Governor George Wallace
发出他的象征性威胁
had carried out his symbolic threat
站在教学楼门口
to stand in the school house door.
我对于那个声明...
I take it from that statement...
伊尔  出什么事了?
Earl, what's going on?
"熊崽"想进这学校
Coons are trying to get into school.
熊崽?  如果浣熊想进我家的后院
Coons? When raccoons tried getting on our back porch,
妈妈会用扫帚赶它们走
Mama just chased them off with a broom.
我不是说浣熊  傻瓜  是黑鬼
Not raccoons, you idiot. Niggers.
他们想和我们一起上学校
And they want to go to school with us.
和我们一起?  他们?
With us? They do?
在华莱士州长
Shortly after Govern or Wallace
将阻塞校门的威胁付诸实施之后
had carried out his promise to block the door way,
肯尼迪下令国防部使用武力
Kennedy ordered these cretary of defense to use military force.
本台播放的录像  是当时在现场
Here, by video tape, is the encounter
国民警卫队指挥官格拉汉将军
by General Graham, commander of the National Guard,
和华莱士州长的冲突
and Governor Wallace.
因为国民警卫队
Because these National Guardsmen
今天是作为亚拉巴马州的联邦士兵
are here today as federal soldiers for Alabama,
他们住在本州境内
and they live within our borders.
他们是我们的兄弟
They are our brothers.
我们已经获得胜利
We are winning in this fight,
因为我们唤醒了美国人民
because we are awakening the American people
去面对我们谈论已久的危机
to the dangers that we have spoken about so many times
今天的事清楚地显示...
that is so evident today...
我们的国家正在走向军事独裁
A trend toward military dictatorship in this country.
就这样  当天傍晚
And so, at day's end,
在图卡卢沙的亚拉巴马大学的隔离被取缔
the University of Alabama in Tuscaloosa had been desegregated,
学生杰米·胡和费文·马隆
and students Jimmy Hood and Vivian Malone
已登记参加夏季的课程学习
had been signed up for summer classes.
太太  你的书掉了
Ma'am, you dropped your book.
太太
Ma'am.
华莱士州长说到做到
Govern or Wallace did what he promised.
在图卡卢沙的校园里  他让人们...
By being on the Tuscaloosa campus, he kept the mob...
喂  那是阿甘吧?
Say, wasn't that Gump?
不  不会的
Naw, that couldn't be.
绝对是他
It sure as hell was.
几年之后
A few years later,
教学楼门口那位坏脾气的小个子
that angry little man at the school house door
觉得去竞选总统是个好主意
thought it'd be a good idea and ran for president.
但有人觉得不是
But somebody thought that it wasn't.
但他没有死
But he didn't die.
我的车到了
My bus is here.
这是9路车吗?
Is it the number 9?
不  这是4路车
No, it's the number 4.
很高兴和你聊天
It was nice talking to you.
我还记得那时候
I remember when that happened,
当华莱士遇刺时
when Wallace got shot.
我还在上大学
I was in college.
你上的是女子大学
Did you go to a girls' college
还是男女都有的大学?
or a girls' and boys' together college?
男女都有
It was coed.
珍妮上的大学我不能去上
'Cause Jenny went to a college I couldn't go to.
那是所女孩子读的大学
It was a college just for girls.
但我一有机会就去看她
But I'd go and visit her every chance I got.
我不知道我为何爱你
I don't know why I love you
可我就是爱
But I do
我不知道我为何哭泣
I don't know why I cry so
可我就是哭
But I do
我只知道我知道...
I only know I know that...
很痛
That hurts.
可我不知道我为何爱你
But I don't know why I love you
可我就是爱
But I do
福雷斯!
Forrest!
福雷斯  住手!
Forrest, stop it!
住手!
Stop it!
你干什么?
What are you doing?
他在伤害你
He was hurting you.
不  他没有!
No, he wasn't!
往那边走!
Get over there!
比利  对不起
Billy, I'm sorry.
请离我远一点
Just keep away from me.
不要这样...  不要走
Don't be such... Don't go.
比利  等一下
Billy, wait a second.
他不懂事
He doesn't know any better.
福雷斯  你为什么那样做?
Forrest, why'd you do that?
我给你带了巧克力来
I brought you some chocolate.
对不起
I'm sorry.
现在我要回我的学校了
I'll go back to my college now.
福雷斯...
Forrest...
瞧你
Look at you.
来吧
Come on.
这是你自己的房间吗?
Is this your own room?
嘘!
Shh!
你有过梦想吗  福雷斯...
Do you ever dream, Forrest...
梦想你将来要成为什么人?
about who you're going to be?
我将来要成为什么人?
Who I'm going to be?
对
Yeah.
我将来不能做我自己了吗?
Aren't I going to be me?
你永远都会是你
You'll always be you,
但会是另一种人
just another kind of you.
你明白吗?
You know?
我想成名
I want to be famous.
我想当个琼·贝兹那样的歌手
I want to be a singer like Joan Baez.
我只想...
I just want to be...
站在空旷的舞台上
on an empty stage
伴着我的吉它  我的歌声
with my guitar, my voice.
只有我自己
Just me.
我想自己去接触大众
And I want to reach people on a personal level.
我想能够谈一些事
I want to be able to say things,
只是两个人之间
just one to one.
你有和女孩子一起过吗  福雷斯?
Have you ever been with a girl, Forrest?
我和她们坐一起
I sit next to them
在家政课的课堂上
in my home economics class all the time.
啊  对不起
Oh, I'm sorry.
没关系  对不起
It's O.K. Sorry.
没关系
It's all right.
It's O.K.
啊  我头晕
Oh, I'm dizzy.
我想你在家政课上没做过这个吧
I'll bet that never happened in home ec.
没有
No.
我想我弄脏了你室友的浴袍
I think I ruined your roommate's bathrobe.
我无所谓  反正我不喜欢她
I don't care. I don't like her anyway.
跑!  跑!  跑!  跑!
Run! Run! Run! Run!
跑!  跑!  跑!  跑!  跑!  跑!
Run! Run! Run! Run! Run! Run!
停!  停!  停!
Stop! Stop! Stop!
大学生活过得真快
College ran by real fast
因为我美式足球打得太多
Because I played so much football.
他们还把我弄进一个什么东西
They even put me on a thing
叫做全美明星队
called the all-America team
那样你可以去见
where you get to meet
合众国的总统
the president of the United States.
肯尼迪总统接见了
President Kennedy met
全美大学足球队
with the collegiate all-American football team
在椭圆形办公室
at the Oval Office today.
那里最棒的一点
Now the really good thing
见合众国的总统的时候
about meeting the president of the United States
是食物
is the food.
他们让你呆在一个小房间里
They put you in this little room
里面有你爱吃或喝任何东西
with just about anything you'd want to eat or drink.
但是  因为第一：
But since, number one,
我不饿但是口渴
I wasn 't hungry but thirsty,
第二  这全是免费的
and number two, they was free,
我大概喝了15瓶汽水
I must have drank me about 15 Dr. Peppers.
入选全美明星队感觉如何?
How does it feel to be an all-American?
很荣幸  先生
It's an honor, sir.
入选全美明星队感觉如何?
How does it feel to be an all-American?
很好  先生
Very good, sir.
入选全美明星队感觉如何?
How does it feel to be an all-American?
很好  先生
Very good, sir.
祝贺你  你感觉如何?
Congratulations. How do you feel?
我想撒尿
I got to pee.
我听着他好象说他想撒尿
I believe he said he had to pee.
不久之后,不知什么原因
Some time later, for noparticular reason,
有人枪杀了这位不错的年轻总统
somebody shot that nice young president
当时他坐着他的车
when he was riding in his car.
又过了几年
And a few years after that,
有人又枪杀了他的弟弟
somebody shot his little brother, too,
这次他是在一个酒店的厨房里
only he was in a hotel kitchen.
做兄弟可真不容易啊
Must be hard being brothers.
我不明白
I wouldn't know.
福雷斯·甘
Forrest Gump.
你相信不相信?
Now can you believe it?
只不过玩了五年足球
After only five years of playing football,
我得到了大学学位
I got a college degree.
祝贺你  孩子
Congratulations, son.
妈妈骄傲极了
Mama was so proud.
福雷斯  我为你骄傲
Forrest, I'm so proud of you.
我替你拿着这个
I'll hold this for you.
祝贺你  孩子
Congratulations, son.
你有没有考虑过你的未来?
Have you given any thought to your future?
考虑?
Thought?
你好  我是福雷斯  福雷斯·甘
Hello. I'm Forrest. Forrest Gump.
根本没人会关心
Nobody gives a horse's shit
你叫什么名字  脓包!
who you are, pus ball!
你还不如低等生物  吃屎的蛆!
You're not even a lowlife, scum-sucking maggot!
你赶快坐到座位上!
Get your maggoty ass on the bus!
你现在到部队了!
You're in the army now!
有人坐了
Seat's taken.
有人
Taken.
开始我觉得我犯了个错误
At first it seemed like I made a mistake.
入伍第一天
It was only my induction day,
我就给骂得狗血喷头
and I was getting yelled at.
你愿意的话可以坐下
Sit down if you want to.
我不知我会遇到谁
I didn't know who I might meet
或他们会问我什么
or what they might ask.
你有没有乘过真正的捕虾船?
You ever been on a real shrimp boat?
没有
No.
可我乘过一条真正的大船
But I been on a real big boat.
我指的是一种专门捕虾的船
I'm talking about a shrimp catching boat.
我一直都在捕虾船上干活
I been working on shrimp boats all my life.
开始是我叔叔的船
I started out on my uncle's boat
那时我大概9岁
when I was about maybe 9.
我刚在考虑自己去买一条船
I was just looking into buying my own boat
然后就应征入伍了
and got drafted.
我的名字叫本杰明·巴弗·布鲁
My given name is Benjamin Buford Blue.
人们都管我叫布巴
People call me Bubba,
好象个乡下佬的名字
just like one of them old red neck boys.
很难以置信吧?
Can you believe that?
我叫福雷斯·甘
My name's Forrest Gump.
人们都管我叫福雷斯·甘
People call me Forrest Gump.
布巴来自亚拉巴州拉巴特湾
So Bubba was from Bayou La Batre, Alabama
他的妈妈是煮虾的
and his mama cooked shrimp.
她的妈妈也是煮虾的
And her mama before her cooked shrimp,
还有她妈妈的妈妈也是煮虾的
and her mama before her mama cooked shrimp, too.
布巴家的人了解所有
Bubba's family knew everything
跟捕虾有关的事情
there was to know about the shrimping business.
我知道所有
I know everything there is to know
跟捕虾有关的事情
about the shrimping business.
我自己也准备去捕虾
I'm going into the shrimping business for myself
等我退伍之后
after I get out of the army.
好的
O.K.
阿甘!
Gump!
你到部队来干什么?
What's your sole purpose in this army?
干你叫我干的事  教官!
To do whatever you tell me, Drill Sergeant!
他妈的  阿甘  你他妈的真是个天才
God damn it, Gump, you're a goddamn genius.
这是我听过的最了不起的回答
That's the most outstanding answer I've ever heard.
你他妈的智商一定有一百六
You must have a goddamn I. Q Of 160.
你他妈的真有天赋  列兵阿甘
You are goddamn gifted, Private Gump.
大家都听着!
Listen up, people!
不知什么原因  我很适合当兵
Now for some reason, I fit in the army
就像如鱼得水一样
Like one of them round pegs.
其实一点都不苦
It's not really hard.
你只需把你的床铺好
You just make your bed neat,
记着要站得笔直
remember to stand up straight,
不管回答什么问题
and always answer every question
都说  "是  教官"
with "Yes, Drill Sergeant."
听清楚没有?
Is that clear?
是  教官!
Yes, Drill Sergeant!
你只需要沿着海底拖你的网
What you do is drag your nets along the bottom.
在一个好天气
On a good day,
你一次就能捕到上百磅的虾
you can catch over a hundred pounds of shrimp.
如果一切顺利
Everything goes all right,
两个人捕10个小时的虾
2 men shrimping 10 hours,
减去你用掉的油费
Less what you spends on gas...
完成了  教官!
Done, Drill Sergeant!
阿甘!
Gump!
为什么你这么快就把枪装好了?
Why did you put that weapon together so quickly?
你叫我这么做的  教官
You told me to, Drill Sergeant.
耶稣基督啊
Jesus Christ.
这是新的连队纪录
This is a new company record.
如果不是因为
If it wasn't a waste
我们这儿兵源不足
of a fine enlisted man,
我会推荐你上军官预备学校  列兵阿甘
I'd recommend you for O.C.S., Private Gump.
有朝一日你会当上将军!
You're going to be a general someday!
现在把你的枪拆开重装一遍!
Now disassemble your weapon and continue!
总之  就象我说过的
Anyway, like I was saying,
虾是海里最好的东西
shrimp is the fruit of the sea.
可以用来烧  煮  烤
You can barbecue it, boil it, broil it,
烘  炒
bake it, saute it.
把它做成串烧虾  克洛虾
They's, uh, shrimp kabobs, shrimp creole,
鲜虾羹  铁板虾  油炸虾
shrimp gumbo, pan fried, deep fried,
脆皮虾
stir fried.
还有菠萝虾
There's pineapple shrimp
柠檬虾  椰子虾
and lemon shrimp, coconut shrimp,
胡椒虾
pepper shrimp,
鲜虾汤  油焖虾
shrimp soup, shrimp stew,
虾肉色拉
shrimp salad,
土豆虾
shrimp in potatoes,
虾肉汉堡包
shrimp burger,
虾肉三明治
shrimp sandwich.
还有...  差不多就这些了
That... That's about it.
军队里晚上有点寂寞
Night time in the army is alonely time.
我们躺在床铺上
We'd lay there in our bunks,
我会想念我的妈妈
and I'd miss my mama,
我也会想念珍妮
and I'd miss Jenny.
嘿  阿甘
Hey, Gump.
瞧她那对奶子
Get a load of the tits on her.
看起来...
Turns out...
珍妮惹上麻烦了
Jenny had gotten in to some trouble
为了几张她穿着校服的照片
over some photos of her in her college sweater.
她被开除学籍
And she was thrown out of school.
我的宝贝在参加女权运动
My baby does the hanky panky
但那也不算坏事
But that wasn't a bad thing,
因为有一位剧院老板
'cause a man who owns a theater
他在田纳西州孟斐斯市
in Memphis, Tennessee,
看了那些照片
saw those photos
就给珍妮一个唱歌的工作
and offered Jenny a job singing in a show.
我一找到机会
The first chance I got,
我就乘车去孟斐斯
I took the bus up to Memphis
去看她表演节目
to see her perform in that show.
那位是安珀  安珀·弗兰
That was Amber, Amber Flame.
请再为她鼓一回掌
Give her a big hand.
接下来的节目你们一定会喜欢
And now, for your listening and viewing pleasure,
来自加州好莱坞
direct from Hollywood, California,
我们的叛逆美女
our very own beatnik beauty.
让我们用最热烈的掌声
Let's give a big round of applause
欢迎这位美丽的女鲍勃迪伦
to the luscious Bobbie Dylan.
一个人要走多少路
How many roads must a man walk down
才能被称为男子汉?
Before you can call him a man?
一条船要出几回海...
Yes, and how many seas must the white dove sail
她的梦想真的实现了
Her dream had come true.
才能在沙滩上安睡?
Before she sleeps in the sand?
她成了一位民谣歌手
She was a folk singer.
而到底需要多少次...
Yes, and how many times
炮火的轰鸣
Must the cannon balls fly
才能结束战争?
Before they're forever banned?
快来点刺激的
Shake it up now.
还是给她一把口琴吧
Somebody get her a harmonica.
那答案  我的朋友...
The answer, my friend
随风飘荡...
Is blowin' in the wind
这可不是儿童节目袋鼠船长
This ain't Captain Kangaroo.
嘿  甜心  我这里有东西要给你
Hey, honey, I got something here for you.
嘿!  去你的!
Hey! God damn it!
嘿  你这傻瓜蛋!
Hey, you stupid jerk!
我在唱歌
I'm singing a song here.
波丽  快走!
Polly, get out here!
你闭嘴!
Shut up yourself!
闭嘴!
Just shut up!
福雷斯  你来干什么?
Forrest! What are you doing here?
你干什么?
What are you doing?
你干什么  福雷斯?
What are you doing, Forrest?
放下我!
Let me down!
你不能老是这样做  福雷斯
You can't keep doing this, Forrest.
你别老是想着要救我
You can't keep trying to rescue me all the time.
他们刚才想抓你
They was trying to grab you.
很多人都想抓我
A lot of people try to grab me.
可是你不能老是这样做
Just... You can't keep doing this all the time.
我忍不住  我爱你
I can't help it. I love you.
福雷斯...
Forrest...
你不知道什么是爱
You don't know what love is.
你还记得我们的祈祷吗  福雷斯?
You remember that time we prayed, Forrest?
我们祈祷上帝把我变成一只鸟
We prayed for God to turn me into a bird
让我能飞得远远的
so I could fly far away.
是的  我记得
Yes, I do.
你认为我能飞下这座桥吗?
You think I could fly off this bridge?
你说什么  珍妮?
What do you mean, Jenny?
没什么
Nothing.
我要离开这里了
I got to get out of here.
等等  珍妮
Wait, Jenny.
福雷斯  你离开我  好吗?
Forrest, you stay away from me, O. K?
请你离开我
You stay away from me, please.
我能搭车吗?
Can I have a ride?
你去哪里?
Where are you going?
我无所谓
I don't care.
上车吧
Get in the truck.
那么再见  珍妮
So bye-bye, Jenny.
他们要送我去越南
They sending me to Vietnam.
那是另外一个国家
It's this whole other country.
请再等一会儿
Just hang on a minute.
听着  你要答应我一件事  好吗?
Listen, you promise me something, O. K?
如果你遇到了麻烦  不要逞能
Just if you're ever in trouble, don't be brave.
你只要跑  好吗?  跑得远远的
You just run, O. K? Just run away.
好吧
O.K.
珍妮
Jenny.
我会经常写信给你
I'll write you all the time.
就是这样  她走了
And just like that, she was gone.
你要平平安安地回来
You come back safe to me.
你听明白了吗?
Do you hear?
有的人生下来
Some folks are born
是为挥舞旗帜
Made to wave the flag
红色白色蓝色
Ooh, they're red, white, and blue
乐队奏起赞歌
And when the band plays "Hail To The Chief"
他们放着礼炮
Ooh, they'll point the cannon at you
那不会是我
It ain't me
我不是高官子弟
I ain't no senator's son
那不会是我
It ain't me
他们告诉我们
Now they told us
越南完全不一样
that Vietnam was going to be very different
和美利坚合众国相比
from the United States of America.
除了啤酒罐和烧烤以外
Except for all the beer cans and barbecues,
的确如此
it was.
嘿  我敢打赌这水里全都是虾
Hey, I'll bet there's shrimp all in these waters.
他们告诉我越南的虾最好
They tell me these Vietnams is good shrimp.
等我们赢了这场战争
After we win this war
我们就接管所有东西
and we take over everything,
我们可以把美国捕虾船开过来
we can get American shrimpers out here
在这水里捕虾
and shrimp these waters.
一天到晚捕虾  兄弟
Just shrimp all the time, man.
你们是新兵吧
You must be my FNGs.
早上好  长官
Morning, sir.
啊  把你们的手放下
Oh, get your hands down.
不要向我敬礼
Do not salute me.
这一带有他妈的很多狙击手
There are goddamn snipers all around this area
最喜欢打军官
who'd love to grease an officer.
我是丹·泰勒中尉  欢迎来弗特排
I'm Lieutenant Dan Taylor. Welcome to Fort Platoon.
你的嘴唇怎么啦?
What's wrong with your lip?
我天生就是厚嘴唇  长官
I was born with big gums, sir.
嗯  你最好把它吸进去点
Well, you better tuck that in.
不然会碰到地雷线
Gonna get that caught on a trip wire.
你们几个是哪里人?
Where are you boys from in the world?
亚拉巴马  长官!  亚拉巴马  长官!
Alabama, sir! Alabama, sir!
你们是双胞胎?
You twins?
不  我们不是亲戚  长官
No. We are not relations, sir.
听着
Look,
这里的基本规矩
it's pretty basic here.
你们跟紧我
You stick with me
一边向其他人学习  他们来这国家有段时间了
and learn from the guys who've been in country a while,
你们会习惯的
you'll be all right.
士兵有一样装备很重要
There is one item of G.I. gear
它关系到你的生死...
that can be the difference between life and death...
袜子
Socks.
底部有衬垫  军绿色
Cushioned sole, O.D. green.
你要保持双脚干燥
Try and keep your feet dry.
我们爬山的时候  要换袜子
When we're out humpin', change your socks
否则停下来的时候
whenever we stop.
湄公河会把你的脚泡烂  整个脚会掉下来
The Mekong will eat a grunt's feet right off his legs.
西斯中士  见鬼
Sergeant Sims. God damn it,
我叫你去领的绳子呢?
where's that sling rope I said to order?
我写到申请单上了
I put in the requisitions.
嗯  你叫那帮狗娘养的...
Well, you call those sons of bitches...
丹中尉很了解他的下属
Lieutenant Dan sure knew his stuff.
能做他的下属我觉得很幸运
I felt real lucky he was my lieutenant.
他来自一个军人世家
He was from a long, great military tradition.
他家族的人曾经分别参加...  并牺牲...
Somebody in his family had fought and died
在...
in every...
每一场...
single...
美国的战争里
American war.
见鬼  抓紧时间
God damn it, kick some ass.
快去做!
Get on it!
我想你可以说  他很有荣誉感
I guess you could say he had a lot to live up to.
那么你们几个是堪萨斯人  是吗?  嗯
So, you boys from Arkansas, huh? Well,
我去过那里
I been through there.
小石城是个好地方
Little Rock's a fine town.
现在放下装备
Now, shake down your gear.
去找排军需官
See the platoon sergeant.
领你要用的东西
Draw what you need for the field.
如果你们几个饿了
If you boys are hungry,
我们这儿正好在烧牛排
we got steaks burning right over here.
我们排有两条守则...
Two standing orders in this platoon...
一: 保护好你的脚
1... take care of your feet,
二:别做任何傻事
2... try not to do anything stupid,
比如让你自己被打死
Like getting yourself killed.
我希望我不会令他失望
I sure hope I don't let him down.
我到了这个国家的很多地方
I got to see a lot of the country side.
我们走了很长的路
We would take these real long walks.
总会有条路
There must be some kind of way
从这里出发
Out of here
小丑告诉贼
Said the joker to the thief
我们总是在找
And we were always lookin'
一个叫"越共"的家伙
for this guy named Charlie.
一切都令人迷惑
There's too much confusion
我什么都不相信
I can't get no relief
停下!  停下  兄弟们!
Hold it up! Hold up, boys!
也不总是很有趣
It wasn't always fun.
丹中尉总是有些奇怪的感觉
Lieutenant Dan was always getting these funny feelings
对于路上的风吹草动
about a rock or a trail or the road,
他会叫我们蹲下  安静
so he'd tell us to get down, shut up.
蹲下!
Get down!
安静!
Shut up!
我们都照做
So we did.
我对什么都不太明白
Now I don't know much about anything,
但我想美国最好的年青人
but I think some of America's best young men
都参加了这场战争
served in this war.
那是非尼克斯来的达拉斯
There was Dallas from Phoenix.
克利夫兰...  他来自底特律
Cleveland... he was from Detroit.
嘿  泰克斯
Hey, Tex.
究竟出什么事了?
What the hell's going on?
泰克斯是...
And Tex was...
嗯  我不记得泰克斯是哪里人了
Well, I don't remember where Tex come from...
啊  没事了
Ah, nothing.
第四排  站起来
Fourth platoon, on your feet.
你们10分钟内赶到河边
Y'all got 10 clicks to go to that river.
出发
Move out.
一二一!
1, 2! Hup!
齐步走!
Step it up!
那边好象不错
Look alive out there.
在越南最好的一点
The good thing about Vietnam
就是总有地方可去
is there was always someplace to go.
当心  危险!
Fire in the hole!
阿甘  搜一下那个洞
Gump, check out that hole.
也总有事情可做
And there was always something to do.
准备好!
Mount'em up!
散开!  掩护他!
Spread out! Cover his back!
有一天开始下雨了
One day it started raining,
然后一直不停的下了四个月
and it didn't quit for four months.
我们经历了各种各样的雨...
We've been through every kind of rain there is...
象小针样的雨
little bitty stinging rain
还有倾盆大雨
and big old fat rain,
从侧面下的雨
rain that flew in side ways,
有时甚至还有
and sometimes rain even seemed
从下往上的雨
to come straight up from underneath.
连晚上也下雨
Shoot, it even rained at night.
嘿  福雷斯
Hey, Forrest.
嘿  布巴
Hey, Bubba.
我的背靠着你的背
I'm going to lean up against you.
你的背靠着你的背
You lean up against me.
这样我们睡着的时候
This way we don't have to sleep
头就不会钻进泥里
with our heads in the mud.
你知道为何我们是好伙伴  福雷斯?
You know why we're a good partnership, Forrest?
因为我们互相照顾
'Cause we be watching out for one another,
就象兄弟一样
like brothers and stuff.
嘿  福雷斯
Hey, Forrest,
我在考虑一件事
something I been thinking about.
我有个很重要的问题要问你
I got a very important question to ask you.
你想不想  和我一起去捕虾?
How would you like to go into the shrimping business with me?
好的
O.K.
兄弟  你听我说
Man, I tell you what.
我全计划好了
I got it all figured out, too.
我们捕到的虾多少磅  拿来付买船的贷款
So many pounds of shrimp will pay off the boat.
多少磅拿来付油费
So many pounds for gas.
我们住在船上就行
We'll live right on the boat.
这样就不用付房租
We ain't got to pay no rent.
我们合伙来干
We can just work it together,
全部都对半分
split everything right down the middle.
兄弟  告诉你  五五分成
Man, I'm telling you, 50-50.
还有  福雷斯  虾可以随便吃
Hey, Forrest, all the shrimp you can eat.
真是个好主意
That's a fine idea.
布巴的主意真得很好
Bubba did have a fine idea.
我甚至写信给珍妮
I even wrote Jenny
告诉她这件事情
and told her all about it.
我给她寄信...
I sent her letters...
差不多每天都寄
Not every day, but almost.
告诉她我在做的事
I told her what I was doing
也问她在做些什么
and asked her what she was doing
告诉她我经常想念她
and told her how I thought about her always.
和我多么希望
And how I was looking forward
能收到她一封回信
to getting a letter from her
只要她有时间
just as soon as she had the time.
我总是告诉她我很平安
I'd always let her know that I was O. K.
然后我的落款总是"爱你的福雷斯·甘"
Then I'd sign each letter "Love, Forrest Gump."
有事情正在发生
There's somethin' happenin' here
那一天  我们象平常一样走着
This one day, we was out walking like always,
然后  忽然之间
and then, just like that,
就象有人关掉天上的水龙头
somebody turned off the rain,
太阳出来了
and the sun come out.
我必须小心
I got to beware
有埋伏!
Ambush!
快找掩护!
Take cover!
快把它拿过来  见鬼
Get that pig up here, god damn it!
福雷斯  你没事吧?
Forrest! You okay?
强手  强手!
Strong-arm, Strong-arm!
嘿!  有个人倒下了!
Hey! We got a man down!
强手  我们是第雷利六号!  完毕!
Strong-arm, this is Leg Lima 6! Over!
收到  强手!  我们遭到袭击
Roger, Strong-arm! Be advised we have incoming
在蓝点树林
from the tree line at point blue
从两个方向!  有冲锋枪和火箭筒!
plus two! A.K. s and rockets!
我们损失惨重!
We're getting it hard!
哑火!  哑火!
Misfire! Misfire!
见鬼!
God damn it!
把那玩意扔掉撤退到树林!
Get that pig unfucked and on the treeline!
他们压住我们了
They got us, and it hurt.
我们准备撤退
We're going to move back to the blue line.
撤退!  撤退!
Pull back! Pull back!
福雷斯!  跑  福雷斯!
Forrest! Run, Forrest!
撤退!
Pull back!
跑!  跑  兄弟!
Run! Run, man!
跑!
Run!
撤退  阿甘!
Pull back, Gump!
跑  见鬼!  跑!
Run, God damn it! Run!
我一直跑  就象珍妮要我做的
I ran and ran just like Jenny told me to.
我跑得这么快这么远
I ran so far so fast
很快就只剩下我一个人
that pretty soon I was all by myself,
这下糟糕了
which was a bad thing.
布巴
Bubba.
布巴是我最好的朋友
Bubba was my best good friend.
我要保证他没事
I had to make sure he was O.K.
你在哪儿?
Where the hell are you?
布巴!
Bubba!
我回去找布巴途中
And on my way back to find Bubba,
发现有个人躺在地上
well, there was this boy laying on the ground.
泰克斯
Tex.
好了
O.K.
我不能让他单独躺在那里  他非常害怕
I couldn't let him lay there all alone, scared the way he was,
所以我扶起他
so I grabbed him up
背他逃出那里
and run him out of there.
每次我回去找布巴
Every time I went back looking for Bubba,
总有人在喊：
somebody else was saying,
"救命  福雷斯  救命!"
"Help me, Forrest, help me!"
好了  好了
O.K. Here. Here.
不要怕  兄弟  躺下  你会没事的
No sweat, man. Lay back. You'll be O.K.
我开始担心我可能永远找不到布巴
I started to get scared that I might never find Bubba.
我知道我的处境
I know my position
越来越危险!
is danger close!
这一带到处都是"越共"
We got Charlie all over this area.
我这儿需要快速的支援  完毕
I got to have those fast movers in here now. Over.
丹中尉  科曼死了!
Lieutenant Dan, Coleman's dead!
我知道他死了!
I know he's dead!
我他妈的整个排全完了!
My whole goddamn platoon is wiped out!
该死的!
God damn it!
你干什么?
What are you doing?
你把我放下!
You leave me here!
走开  把我留在这里!
Get away. Just leave me here!
走开!
Get out!
啊!  我说把我留在这儿  该死的!
Aah! God, I said leave me here, God damn it!
雷利  我是强手
Leg Lima, this is Strong-arm.
我们马上提供快速支援  完毕
Be advised your fast movers are in bound. Over.
突然好象有什么东西跳起来咬我
Then it felt like something just jumped up and bit me.
啊!  什么东西在咬我!
Aah! Something bit me!
你这狗娘养的!
You son of a bitch!
我不能离开我的排
I can't leave the platoon.
我叫你把我留在那里  阿甘
I told you to leave me there, Gump.
丢下我  你自己逃吧!
Forget about me. Get your self out!
你听到我的话没有?
Did you hear what I said?
阿甘  见鬼  放下我
Gump, damn it, put me down.
你自己逃吧
Get your ass out of here.
我没叫你救我出去  去你妈的!
I didn't ask you to pull me out of there, God damn you!
你又要去哪里?
Where the hell do you think you're going?
去找布巴
To get Bubba.
我已经呼叫空袭了
I got an air strike in bound right now.
他们会把那里炸平
They're going to nape the whole area.
留在这里!  这是命令
Stay here! That's an order.
我要找到布巴!
I gotta find Bubba!
福雷斯
Forrest.
布巴
Bubba.
我没事  福雷斯
I'm O.K., Forrest.
我没事
I'm O.K.
啊  布巴  不
O-Oh, Bubba, no.
我没事的
I'll be all right.
行了
Come on.
行了  行了
Come on. Come on.
我没事  福雷斯
Ugh. I'm O.K., Forrest.
我没事  我很好
I'm O.K. I'm fine.
炸平那里
Top smoke. Get it up there.
如果我知道这将是
If I'd have known this was going to be
我和布巴的最后一次谈话
the last time me and Bubba was gonna talk,
我会想些更好的话来说
I'd of thought of something better to say.
嘿  布巴
Hey, Bubba.
嘿  福雷斯
Hey, Forrest.
福雷斯...
Forrest...
出什么事了?
Why did this happen?
你中弹了
You got shot.
布巴说了一句我永远不会忘记的话
Then Bubba said something I won't ever forget.
我想回家
I want to go home.
布巴是我最好的好朋友
Bubba was my best good friend.
我还知道
And even I know
好朋友不是那么容易找到的
that ain't something you can find just around the corner.
布巴想当一个捕虾船的船长
Bubba was going to be a shrimping boat captain,
但是  他却死在越南的一条河边
but instead, he died right there by that river in Vietnam.
我要说的就是这些了
That's all I have to say about that.
那是粒子弹  是吗?
It was a bullet, wasn't it?
子弹?
A bullet?
跳起来咬你的那个东西
That jumped up and bit you.
啊  对  先生
Oh. Yes, sir.
正好咬在我屁股上
Bit me directly in the but-tocks.
他们说这样的伤口价值百万  但...
They said it was a million dollar wound, but...
那些钱大概是被军队留着了
the army must keep that money,
因为那一百万我至今连半毛钱也没看见
because I still ain't seen a nickel of that million dollars.
屁股受伤的唯一好处
The only good thing about being wounded in the but-tocks
是冰淇淋
is the ice cream.
我能吃多少冰淇淋他们就给我多少
They gave me all the ice cream I could eat.
你猜怎么着?
And guess what?
我的一位好朋友就在隔壁床上
A good friend of mine was in the bed right next door.
丹中尉  我给你拿冰淇淋来了
Lieutenant Dan, I got you some ice cream.
丹中尉  冰淇淋!
Lieutenant Dan, ice cream!
你该洗澡了  中尉
It's time for your bath, Lieutenant.
哈珀!
Harper!
库珀
Cooper.
拉森
Larson.
韦斯特
Webster.
阿甘
Gump.
阿甘!
Gump!
我是福雷斯·甘
I'm Forrest Gump.
凯利
Kyle.
尼科斯
Nichols.
麦克米尔
McMill.
约翰逊
Johnson.
惊喜  惊喜  惊喜!
Surprise, surprise, surprise!
阿甘  你怎么能看这种狗屎节目?
Gump, how can you watch that stupid shit?
把它关掉
Turn it off.
你正在收看美军台  越南电视网
You are tuned to the American forces Vietnam network.
这是西贡台6频道
This is channel 6, Saigon.
接得好  阿甘
Good catch, Gump.
你知道怎么打吗?
You know how to play this?
来  我教你
Come on. Let me show you.
打乒乓球的关键就是
Now, the secret to this game is
无论发生什么事
no matter what happens,
永远不要...
never, ever...
把目光离开球
take your eye off the ball.
好吧
All right.
不知为什么
For some reason,
我天生是打乒乓的料
Ping-Pong came very natural to me.
看见了?
See?
连傻瓜也会打
Any idiot can play.
于是我开始经常打球
So I started playing it all the time.
我打乒乓球
I played Ping-Pong
甚至没人陪着也能打
even when I didn't have anyone to play Ping-Pong with.
医院里的人
The hospital's people
说我就象下了水的鸭子...
said it made me look like a duck in water...
不管那是什么意思
Whatever that means.
但连丹中尉也来看我打球
Even Lieutenant Dan would come and watch me play.
我打了这么多的乒乓球
I played Ping-Pong so much,
连睡觉时也在打
I even played it in my sleep.
现在...
Now...
听我说
you listen to me.
我们都有自己的命运
We all have a destiny.
没什么事是完全偶然的  它总有缘故
Nothing just happens. It's all part of a plan!
我应该和我的士兵一起死在那儿
I should have died out there with my men,
但现在...  我只是个他妈的残废人
but now... I'm nothing but a god damn cripple,
没腿的怪物!
a legless freak!
看着我!
Look. Look! Look at me!
你看见没有?
You see that?
你知不知道
Do you know what it's like
没有腿是什么感觉?
not to be able to use your legs?
是  长官  我知道
Y-Y -Yes, sir, I do.
你清楚我的话没有?
Did you hear what I said?
你害了我!
You cheated me!
我有自己的命运
I had a destiny.
我本该死在战场上
I was supposed to die in the field
带着荣誉!
with honor!
那才是我的命运
That was my destiny,
而你...  使我得不到它!
and you... cheated me out of it!
你听明白我的话了吗  阿甘?
You understand what I'm saying, Gump?
本来不应该是这样...
This wasn't supposed to happen...
我不应该这样
Not to me.
我有自己的命运
I had a destiny.
我曾经是...
I was...
中尉军官...
Lieutenant...
丹泰勒
Dan Taylor.
你仍然是
Y-You still
丹中尉
Lieutenant Dan.
看着我
Look at me.
现在我能做什么?
What am I going to do now?
列兵阿甘?
PFC Gump?
是  长官!
Yes, sir!
因为你的表现
As you were.
孩子
Son,
你获得荣誉勋章
you been awarded the Medal of Honor.
你知道吗  丹中尉?
Guess what, Lieutenant Dan?
他们要给我勋...
They want to give me a med...
太太
Ma'am.
丹中尉怎么了?
What did they do with Lieutenant Dan?
他们送他回家了
They sent him home.
两星期后  我离开越南
Two weeks later, I left Vietnam.
典礼已经开始
The ceremony was kicked off
首先是总统的演说
with a can did speech by the president
关于扩大越南战争的必要性
regarding the need for further escalation of the war in Vietnam.
约翰逊总统给四名军人颁发了荣誉勋章
Johnson awarded 4 Medals of Honor to men from each of the armed services.
美国深深地感谢你  孩子
America owes you a debt of gratitude, son.
我知道你受过伤
I understand you were wounded.
你的伤口在哪儿?
Where were you hit?
在屁股上  先生
In the but-tocks, sir.
嗯  那一定很好看
Well, that must be a sight.
我倒想瞧一瞧
I'd kinda like to see that.
我献歌给你  罗宾森太太
And here's to you, Mrs. Robinson
耶稣对你也特别垂青
Jesus loves you more than you will know
上帝保佑你  罗宾森太太
God bless you, please, Mrs. Robinson
老天  这孩子!
God damn, son!
然后妈妈回酒店休息
After that, Mama went to the hotel to lay down,
我出去在我们的首都随处走走
so I went out for a walk to see our nation's capital.
希拉里!  我找了兽医来
Hilary! I got the vets.
你找他们做什么?
What do you want to do with them?
妈妈就应该休息
It's a good thing Mama was resting,
因为街上人挤得要死
'cause the streets was awful crowded with people
他们来看那些雕像和纪念碑
lookin'at all the statues and monuments,
有些人吵吵嚷嚷的
and some of them people were loud and pushy.
好了  跟着我!
O.K., follow me!
不管去哪里  我都要排队
Everywhere I went, I had to stand in line.
快点
Come on.
走!
Go!
嘿  你这么做太对了
Hey, you're a good man for doing this.
很好
Good.
好
O.K.
那儿有这么个人在演讲
There was this man giving a little talk.
不知什么原因
And for some reason,
他身上穿着美国国旗
he was wearing an American flag for a shirt.
他还很爱说"操"...
And he liked to say the "F" word... a lot.
操这个、操那个
"F" this and "F" that.
每次他说"操"
And every time he said the "F" word,
人们不知什么原因就一阵欢呼
people, for some reason, well, they cheered.
对!  对!
Yeah! Yeah!
来  兄弟  上来  兄弟
Come on, man. Come up here, man.
过来  过来
Come on. Come on.
对  你!  过来  快!
Yeah, you! Come on. Move, move!
快  我们上去
Go on. Let's get up there.
给我们讲讲这场战争吧  兄弟
Tell us a little bit about the war, man.
越南的战争?
The war in Vietnam?
就是这场...
The war in Viet-
...操他妈的越南战争!
fucking-nam!
嗯...
Well...
我能说的只有一件事
There was only one thing I could say
关于越南战争
about the war in Vietnam.
我能说的只有一件事关于...
There's only one thing I can say about...
越南战争
the war in Vietnam.
在越南...
In Vietnam...
你在干什么...
What the hell are you do...
我打死你  你这该死的猪头!
I'll beat your head in, you goddamn oinker!
天那!  他究竟是怎么搞的?
Jesus Christ! What did they do with this?
听不见!
Can't hear you!
什么也听不见
Can't hear anything!
这个...  这个!
This... This one!
给我那个!
Give me that!
大声点!
Speak up!
我要说的就是...
And that's all I have to say
这些
about that.
说得很好  兄弟
That's so right on, man.
你说得很好
You said it all.
你叫什么名字  兄弟?
What's your name, man?
我叫福雷斯  福雷斯·甘
My name is Forrest. Forrest Gump.
福雷斯·甘
Forrest Gump.
阿甘!  阿甘!
Gump! Gump! Gump!
福雷斯!
Forrest!
珍妮!
Jenny!
福雷斯!
Forrest!
这是我一生中最快乐的时刻
It was the happiest moment of my life.
我和珍妮又能在一起了
Jenny and me were just like peas and carrots again.
她带我四处逛
She showed me around
介绍她的新朋友给我认识
and even in troduced me to some of her new friends.
拉帘子  兄弟!
Shut that blind, man!
不要靠近窗子
And get your white ass away from that window.
你知不知道我们正在打仗吗?
Don't you know we in a war here?
他很酷  他是我们自己人
He's cool. He's one of us.
让我告诉你我们的情况
Let me tell you about us.
我们在此的目的是保护我们的黑人领袖
Our purpose here is to protect our black leaders
免得他们受到白种猪的袭击
from the racial on slaught of the pig
他们想要伤害我们的黑人领袖
who wishes to brutalize our black leaders,
强奸我们的女人  摧毁我们黑人社区
rape our women, and destroy our black communities.
这怪人是谁?
Who's the baby killer?
这是我跟你提起过的好朋友
This is my good friend I told you about.
这是福雷斯·甘  福雷斯  这是威斯利
This is Forrest Gump. Forrest, this is Wesley.
威斯利和我一起住在伯克利
Wesley and I lived together in Berkeley,
他是学生民主社团伯克利分部主席
and he's the president of the Berkeley chapter of SDS.
我们是来提供保护与帮助
We are here to offer protection and help
为任何需要我们帮助的人
for all those who need our help,
因为我们  黑豹党
because we, the Black Panthers,
是反对越南战争的
are against the war in Vietnam.
我们反对任何战争
We are against any war
黑人士兵总被送往前线
where black soldiers are sent to the front line
为一个仇恨他们的国家送死
to die for a country that hates them.
我们反对任何派黑人士兵去打仗的战争
We are against any war where black soldiers go to fight
这样会毁掉他们自己的社区
and come to be brutalized and killed in their own communities.
我们反对种族主义和帝国主义行为
We are against these racist and imperial acts...
我给她一支枪
And I gave her the gun
我给她一枪
I shot her
福雷斯
Forrest!
停手!
Stop it!
福雷斯!
Forrest!
停手!
Stop it!
我不该带你来这里
I shouldn't have brought you here.
我早该知道大家会争吵!
I should have known it was going to be some bullshit hassle!
他不该打你  珍妮
He should not be hitting you, Jenny.
走吧  福雷斯
Come on, Forrest.
对不起我在你们黑豹党聚会上打架
Sorry I had a fight in the middle of your Black Panther party.
他不是故意这么做的
He doesn't mean it when he does things like this.
我永远也不会伤害你  珍妮
I would never hurt you, Jenny.
我知道你不会,福雷斯
I know you wouldn't, Forrest.
我想成为你的男友
I wanted to be your boy friend.
这件制服不错  福雷斯
That uniform is a trip, Forrest.
你穿起来很帅
You look handsome in it.
真的
You do.
你知道吗?
You know what?
什么?
What?
很开心我们俩能一起到首都来
I'm glad we were here together in our nation's capital.
我也是  福雷斯
Me, too, Forrest.
我们整晚到处逛  我和珍妮
We walked around all night, Jenny and me,
聊天
just talkin'.
她告诉我她所有的旅行
She told me about all the traveling she'd done
她如何发现了新的思想
and how she discovered ways to expand her mind
学习怎样在和谐中生活...
and learn how to live in harmony...
和谐那地方一定是在我们西边
which must be out west somewhere,
因为她一路去到了加州
'cause she made it all the way to California.
去爱另一个人
Love one another right now
有人想去旧金山吗?
Anybody want to go to San Francisco?
我要去
I'll go.
走啦!
Far out!
这是很特别的一晚
It was a very special night
对于我们俩来说
for the two of us.
我真的不想今晚结束
I didn't want it to end.
希望你不走  珍妮
Wish you wouldn't go, Jenny.
我必须走  福雷斯
I have to, Forrest.
珍妮?
Jenny?
所有的事都乱套了
Things got a little out of hand.
都是因为这场战争
It's just this war
还有爱撒谎的约翰逊总统和...
and that lying son of a bitch Johnson and...
我永远不会伤害你  你知道的
I would never hurt you. You know that.
想知道我怎么想吗?
Know what I think?
我想...
I think...
你应该回绿茵镇的家
you should go home to Greenbow,
亚拉巴马!
Alabama!
福雷斯
Forrest,
我们的人生完全不同  你知道
we have very different lives, you know.
我希望你...
I want you...
收下这个
to have this.
福雷斯  我不能接受这个
Forrest, I can't keep this.
我能得到它...
I got it...
都是因为我做了你叫我做的事
just by doing what you told me to do.
你为何对我这么好?
Why are you so good to me?
你是我的女友
You're my girl.
我永远都是你的女友
I'll always be your girl.
什么都在改变改变改变
To everything, turn, turn, turn
这是个改变改变改变的季节
There is a season, turn, turn, turn
为了任何目标而开始的时刻
And a time to every purpose
在整个世界
Under heaven
就是这样
And just like that,
她再次离开我的生活
she was gone out of my life again.
这是个人的一小步
That's one small step for man,
人类的一大步
one giant leap for mankind.
我以为我要回越南去
I thought I was going back to Vietnam,
但他们又觉得
but instead they decided
我对付共产党的最好办法
the best way for me to fight the Communists
是打乒乓球
was to play Ping-Pong,
于是我接受了一个特别任务
so I was in the special Services,
走遍全国
traveling around the country,
慰劳负伤的老兵  为他们表演
cheering up wounded veterans and showing'em
怎么打乒乓球
how to play Ping-Pong.
我打得很好  所以几年后
I was so good that some years later,
军队又觉得我应该  加入全美乒乓球队
the army decided I should be on the all-American Ping-Pong team.
我们是第一批访问中国大陆的美国人
We were the first Americans to visit the land of China
大约一百万年以来
in a million years or something.
有人说世界和平就在我们手中
Somebody said world peace was in our hands,
但我所做的只不过是打乒乓球
but all I did was play Ping-Pong.
回家以后  我成了全国有名的人物
When I got home, I was a national celebrity,
比袋鼠船长还要有名
famouser even than Captain Kangaroo.
这位就是福雷斯·甘
Here he is, Forrest Gump.
在这儿
Right here.
阿甘  请坐
Gump, have a seat.
福雷斯·甘  这位是约翰·列侬
Forrest Gump, John Lennon.
欢迎你回国
Welcome home.
你能不能告诉我们  嗯
Can you tell us, um,
中国是怎么样的?
what was China like?
在中国大陆...
In the land of China...
人们差不多什么都没有
people hardly got nothin'at all.
没有财产?
No possessions?
在中国  他们不去教堂
And in China, they never go to church.
也没有宗教?
No religion, too?
难以想象
Hard to imagine.
嗯  只要你肯试着想象  迪克
Well, it's easy if you try, Dick.
几年以后
Some years later,
那位从英格兰来的好年青人
that nice young man from England
他回家去看他的孩子
was on his way home to see his little boy
半路上在给人签名
and was signing some autographs.
完全没什么原因
For no particular reason at all,
有人枪杀了他
Somebody shot him.
他们给你...
They gave you...
国会荣誉勋章
the congressional Medal of Honor.
啊  是丹中尉
Now, that's Lieutenant Dan.
丹中尉!
Lieutenant Dan!
他们给你...
They gave you...
国会荣誉勋章
the congressional Medal of Honor.
是的  长官  他们是给我了
Yes, sir. They surely did.
他们给你
They gave you,
你这傻瓜
an imbecile,
让你这白痴上电视
a moron who goes on television
让你去出丑
and makes a fool out of himself
在整个该死的国家面前
in front of the whole damn country,
国会荣誉勋章
the Congressional Medal of Honor.
是的  长官
Yes, sir.
嗯  真是...  真是太妙了!
Well... that... that's just perfect!
嗯  我对此只能说一句话...
Yeah, well, I just got one thing to say to that...
上帝诅咒美国
Goddamn bless America.
啊  天哪
Oh, God, whoa!
啊  天哪!
Ow! Oh! Oh, God!
丹中尉!
Lieutenant Dan!
丹中尉说他住在一家旅馆里
Lieutenant Dan said he was living in a hotel
因为他没有腿
and because he didn't have no legs,
他花很多时间练习他们手臂
he spent most of his time exercising his arms.
向右转  向右!
Make a right. Take a right!
你在纽约做什么  丹中尉?
What do you do here in New York, Lieutenant Dan?
我在吃政府救济
I'm living off the government tit.
嗨  你瞎眼了吗?
Hey, hey, hey, are you blind?
我正在走路!
I'm walking here!
出来!
Ah, get out!
行了  走吧!
Come on. Go, go, go!
我和丹中尉在一起
I stayed with Lieutenant Dan
庆祝假期
and celebrated the holidays.
你们过了美好的一年  快回家吧
You have a great year, and hurry home.
上帝保佑你
God bless you.
你找到耶稣了吗  阿甘?
Have you found Jesus yet, Gump?
我不知道我应该去找他  长官
I didn't know I was supposed to be looking for Him, sir.
从越南回来的残废军人
That's all these cripples down at the V. A...
他们都这么说
That's all they ever talk about.
耶稣这个耶稣那个  哈
Jesus this and Jesus that. Ha.
我...  找到耶稣了吗?
Have I... found Jesus?
他们还叫了个牧师来和我聊天
They even had a priest come and talk to me.
他说上帝在听着
He said God is listening,
但我只能顾到自己
but I have to help myself.
如果我的心能接受耶稣
Now, if I accept Jesus into my heart,
我就可以与他在天国同行
I'll get to walk beside Him in the kingdom of heaven.
你听到我说的话了吗?
Did you hear what I said?
同行...
Walk...
与他在天国同行
beside Him in the kingdom of heaven.
嗯...  去你妈的
Well... kiss my crippled ass.
上帝在听着?
God is listening?
全是狗屁
What a crock of shit.
我要上天堂  丹中尉
I'm going to heaven, Lieutenant Dan.
哦?
Oh?
好...
Well...
你去以前...  能不能
before you go... why don't you
起身去街角
get your ass down to the corner
帮我再打点酒?
and get us more Ripple?
是  长官
Yes, sir.
我们大概是在
We're at approximately
纽约市45大街温阿斯特广场
45th Street in New York City at One Astor Plaza.
这个地方就是...
This is the site of the old...
拉巴特湾有什么东西?
What the hell is in Bayou La Batre?
有捕虾船
Shrimping boats.
捕虾船?  捕虾船关我什么事?
Shrimping boats? Who gives a shit about shrimping boats?
我一定要买一条  等我有了钱
I got to buy me one soon as I have some money.
我在越南答应过布巴的
I promised Bubba in Vietnam
等战争结束  我们合伙捕虾
that as soon as the war was over, we'd be partners.
他当船长  我当大副
He'd be the captain and I'd be his first mate.
但他已经死了  我只好当船长
But now that he's dead, I got to be the captain.
捕虾船的船长
A shrimp boat captain.
是  长官  要信守诺言  丹中尉
Yes, sir. A promise is a promise, Lieutenant Dan.
你听听!
Now hear this!
列兵阿甘  要当捕虾船的船长
Private Gump here is gonna be a shrimp boat captain.
嗯  你听着  吹牛大王
Well, I tell you what, Gilligan.
等你当上捕虾船的船长那一天
The day that you are a shrimp boat captain,
我就来当你的大副
I will come and be your first mate.
如果你能当捕虾船的船长
If you're ever a shrimp boat captain,
我就能当宇航员了!
that's the day I'm an astronaut!
阿丹  你说什么?
Danny, what are you complaining about?
阿丹  你好吗?
Danny, how you doing, huh?
轮椅先生!
Mr. Hot Wheels!
这是你的朋友吗?
Who's your friend?
我叫福雷斯  福雷斯·甘
My name is Forrest. Forrest Gump.
这是可爱的卡拉
This is cunning Carla
这是长腿的莱诺
and long-limbs Lenore.
你去哪儿了  宝贝?
So where you been, baby cakes, huh?
最近一直没见你
Haven't seen you around lately.
你应该在这儿过圣诞节的
You should have been here for Christmas,
汤米请大伙喝酒  每人一块火鸡三明治
'cause Tommy bought a free round and gave everybody a turkey sandwich.
嗯  我遇见了...  朋友
Well, well, I had, uh... company.
嘿!  我们刚刚去过那儿!
Hey! Hey, we was just there!
那好象是时代广场
That's like Times Square.
你不喜欢过新年吗?
Don't you just love New Year's?
你能够重新开始
You can start all over.
每人都有新的机会
Everybody gets a second chance.
很奇怪...
It's funny...
在这欢乐的气氛中
but in the middle of all that fun,
我想起了珍妮
I began to think about Jenny,
不知她会如何庆祝除夕夜
wondering how she was spending her New Year's night
在加州
out in California.
你对她不再有爱了吗?
Don't you love her ways?
告诉我你的回答
Tell me what you say
你对她的爱不再疯狂?
Don't you love her madly?
不想去见她父亲?
Want to meet her daddy?
你不再爱她的脸庞了吗?
Don't you love her face?
你不再爱正在离开的她?
Don't you love her as she's walkin' out the door?
九...  八...
9... 8...
七...  六...
7... 6...
五...  四...
5... 4...
三...  二...
3... 2...
一!
1!
新年快乐!
Happy new year!
怎能忘记旧日朋友
Should auld acquaintance be forgot
心中能不怀想?
And never brought to mind?
新年快乐  丹中尉!
Happy new year, Lieutenant Dan!
怎能忘记旧日朋友
Should auld acquaintance be forgot
友谊地久天长!
In days of auld lang syne!
我们站到一起
Together we stand
分开只有失败
Divided we fall
大家一起来吧
Come on now, people, let's
一起生活
Get on the ball
一起工作
And work together
来吧  来吧
Come on, come on
让我们一起工作
Let's work together
啊!  你怎么搞的  你是傻瓜吗?
Oh! What are you, stupid or something?
你有什么毛病?
What's your problem?
他有什么毛病?
What's his problem?
你把你那玩意丢在战场上了吗?
Did you lose your packet in the war or something?
你朋友是不是傻瓜呀?
Is your friend stupid or something?
你说什么?
What did you say?
我说你朋友是不是傻瓜?
I said is your friend stupid or something?
不许叫他傻瓜!
Don't call him stupid!
嘿  不许推她!
Hey, don't push her!
你闭嘴!
You shut up!
绝对不许叫他傻瓜!
Don't you ever call him stupid!
得啦  宝贝  你干嘛这么生气?
Come on, baby, why you being so upset, huh?
穿让你那该死的衣服
Get your goddamned clothes
马上滚你妈的蛋!
and get the hell out of here!
你应该去马戏团
You should be in a sideshow.
瞧你这惨样!
You're so pathetic!
马上滚!
Get out of here!
你这大混蛋!
You big guy!
失败者  怪物!
Loser. You freak!
啊  不
Oh, no. No.
对不起  我毁了  你的新年聚会  丹中尉
I'm sorry I ruined your New Year's Eve party, Lieutenant Dan.
她身上有一股烟味
She tastes like cigarettes.
我想丹中尉发现
I guess Lieutenant Dan figured
有些事你是无法改变的
there's some things you just can't change.
他不想被称为残废
He didn't want to be called crippled
就象我不想被称为傻瓜
just like I didn't want to be called stupid.
新年快乐  阿甘
Happy new year, Gump.
美国乒乓球队
The U.S. Ping-Pong team
今天与尼克松总统见面...
met with President Nixon today...
你知道吧?
Wouldn't you know it?
几个月后
A few months later,
他们邀请我和乒乓球队
they invited me and the Ping-Pong team
去白宫
to visit the White House.
所以我去了...
So I went...
第二次去
again.
并且第二次见到了合众国的总统
And I met the president of the United States again.
不过这次他们没有给我们安排
Only this time, they didn't get us rooms
酒店套房
in a real fancy hotel.
你玩得愉快吗  在我们的首都  年轻人?
Are you enjoying yourself in our nation's capital, young man?
你住在哪儿?
where are you staying?
埃伯特酒店
It's called the Hotel Ebbott.
啊  不  不  我知道有家更好的酒店
Oh, no, no, no. I know a much nicer hotel.
是新开张的水门酒店  设备很先进
It's brand-new. Very modern.
我会叫人安排你入住的
I'll have my people take care of it.
保安
Security.
是  先生
Yeah. Sir,
你能不能叫人维修人员
you might want to send a maintenance man
去对面办公室看看
over to that office across the way.
里面灯不亮
The lights are off
他们大概正在找保险丝盒
and they must be looking for a fuse box,
因为他们打着手电  把我都照醒了
'cause them flashlights, they're keeping me awake.
好的  先生  我去查一下
O.K., sir. I'll check it out.
谢谢  晚安
Thank you. Good night.
因此...
Therefore...
我将辞去总统职位
I shall resign the presidency
从明天中午起生效
effective at noon tomorrow.
福特副总统
Vice President Ford
将宣誓就任总统
will be sworn in as president
明天此时在这间办公室
at that hour in this office.
福雷斯·甘
Forrest Gump.
是  长官!
Yes, sir!
根据条例
As you were.
我收到你的退役批文
I have your discharge papers.
服役期结束了  孩子
Service is up, son.
是不是说我不能再打乒乓球了?
Does this mean I can't play Ping-Pong no more?
对军队来说  是的
For the army, it does.
就这样
And just like that,
我在合众国军队的生活结束了
my service in the United States Army was over.
所以我回家
So I went home.
我回家了  妈妈
I'm home, Mama.
我知道  我知道
I know. I know.
露西  他来了
Louise, he's here.
当我回家时  我不知道做什么
Now, when I got home, I had no idea,
但妈妈有很多访客
but Mama had all sorts of visitors.
我们有客人来访
We've had all sorts of visitors.
每个人都想要你用他们的乒乓器材
Everybody wants you to use their Ping-Pong stuff.
有个人还留了一张两万五的支票
One man even left a check for $25,000
希望你能说：你爱用他们的球拍
if you'd be agree able to saying you like using their paddle.
我只爱用我自己的球拍
I only like using my own paddle.
嗨  露西小姐
Hi, Miss Louise.
嘿  福雷斯
Hey, Forrest.
我知道  可那是两万五啊  福雷斯
I know that, but it's $25,000, Forrest.
我想也许你可以试用一段时间
I thought maybe you could hold it for a while,
看看顺不顺手
see if it grows on you.
妈妈的确说得对
That Mama, she sure was right.
事情总是出乎意料
It's funny how things work out.
我在家没有待太久
I didn't stay home for long
因为我答应过布巴
because I'd made apromise to Bubba,
我总要信守我的诺言
and I always try to keep my promise,
所以我去了拉巴特湾  去见布巴的家人
so I went on down to Bayou La Batre to meet Bubba's family.
你是疯子还是傻瓜?
Are you crazy or just plain stupid?
做傻事的才是傻瓜  布鲁太太
Stupid is as stupid does, Mrs. Blue.
我想也是
I guess.
当然
And, of course,
我也去看望了布巴本人
I paid my respect to Bubba himself.
嘿  布巴  是我  福雷斯·甘
Hey, Bubba. It's me, Forrest Gump.
我记得你说过的话  我已经安排好了
I remember everything you said, and I got it all figured out.
我带来两万四千五百六十二块四毛七分
I'm taking $24,562.47
这是我所有的钱
that I got, that's left
其它钱用来理发和买新衣服
after a new hair cut and a new suit
还有带妈妈上街吃了一顿好饭
and took Mama out to a real fancy dinner,
还买了车票  还买了三瓶汽水
and I bought a bus ticket, then three Dr. Peppers.
告诉我
Tell me something.
你是傻瓜吗?
Are you stupid or something?
做傻事的才是傻瓜  先生
Stupid is as stupid does, sir.
我拿到这些钱是因为我说：
That's what's left after me saying,
"我和全美乒乓球队在中国时
"When I was in China on the all-America Ping-Pong team,
"我最喜欢打乒乓球...
"I just loved playing Ping-Pong
"用我的菲利奥莱乒乓球拍"
with my Flex-O-Lite Ping-Pong paddle,"
谁都知道这不是真话
which everybody knows isn't true,
但妈妈说它只是一个善意的谎话
but Mama said it was just a little white lie,
它不会伤害任何人
so it wasn't hurting nobody.
总之  剩下的钱我全部用来
So anyway, I'm putting all that
买燃料  绳索和网具
on gas, ropes, and new nets
以及一条全新的捕虾船
and a brand-new shrimping boat.
布巴告诉过我所有和捕虾有关的事情
Now Bubba told me everything he knew about shrimping,
但你知道我有什么发现吗?
but you know what I found out?
捕虾很难的
Shrimping is tough.
我只捕到五只
I only caught five.
再来两只  你就能做串烧虾了
A couple more, you can have yourself a cocktail.
嘿  你有没有想过该为这条船命名?
Hey, you ever think about naming this old boat?
船没有名字就没有好运气
It's bad luck to have a boat without a name.
我以前从来没有给船命名
I'd never named a boat before,
我能想起的只有一个名字
but there was only one I could think of,
世界上最美丽的名字
the most beautiful name in the wide world.
跳跳舞
Do a little dance
谈谈情
Make a little love
度过今晚
Get down tonight
跳跳舞
Do a little dance
谈谈情
Make a little love
度过今晚
Get down tonight
度过今晚...
Get down tonight...
我没听到珍妮的消息  已经很久了
Now, I hadn't heard from Jenny in a long while,
但我仍经常想念她
but I thought about her a lot.
不管她在做什么  我希望她开心
I hoped whatever she was doing made her happy.
你不能改变那只小鸟
Oh, and the bird you cannot change
你不能改变这只小鸟
And this bird you cannot change
上天知道我无法改变
Lord knows I can't change
上天保佑我无法改变
Lord, help me, I can't change
我时刻想念着珍妮
I thought about Jenny all the time.
丹中尉  你来做什么?
Lieutenant Dan, what are you doing here?
嗯  我想到海中施展拳脚
Well, thought I'd try out my sea legs.
可是你没有脚了  丹中尉
Well, you ain't got no legs, Lieutenant Dan.
是的  我知道
Yes, I know that.
你写了封信给我  白痴
You wrote me a letter, you idiot.
好了  福雷斯·甘船长
Well, well. Captain Forrest Gump.
我要亲眼来看看...
I had to see this for myself...
并且...
and...
我说过如果你能当捕虾船的船长
I told you if you were ever a shrimp boat captain,
我就来当你的大副
that I'd be your first mate.
所以我来了
Well, here I am.
我是信守诺言的
I'm a man of my word.
好的
O.K.
但你别以为
But don't you be thinking
我会叫你长官
that I'm going to be calling you "sir."
不用  长官
No, sir.
这是我的船
It's my boat.
我觉得如果我们向东开
I have a feeling if we head due east,
我们就会找到虾  现在左转
we'll find some shrimp, so take a left.
向左转!
Take a left!
哪边?
Which way?
那边!
Over there!
他们在那边!
They're over there!
快打舵盘向左
Get on the wheel and take a left.
好的
O.K.
阿甘  你干什么?
Gump, what are you doing?
向左转!
Take a left!
左边!
Left!
那边我们会找到虾的  兄弟!
That's where we're going to find those shrimp, my boy!
那边我们会找到它们
That's where we'll find them.
还是没有虾  丹中尉
Still no shrimp, Lieutenant Dan.
好吧  我弄错了
O.K., so I was wrong.
嗯  我们怎么才能找到虾呢?
Well, how are we going to find them?
也许你可以去祷告
Maybe you should just pray for shrimp.
所以我们祷告
So pray that
我在回家路上...
I'm homeward bound...
所以我每个星期天都去教堂
So I went to church every Sunday.
有时丹中尉也来
Sometimes Lieutenant Dan came, too,
虽然他只让我负责祷告
though I think he left the praying up to me.
没有虾
No shrimp.
你那上帝到底在哪儿?
Where the hell's this God of yours?
奇怪的是丹中尉一说这话
It's funny Lieutenant Dan said that
上帝就来了
'cause right then God showed up.
你绝不能弄沉这条船!
You'll never sink this boat!
我当时很害怕
Now, me, I was scared,
但丹中尉  他象是发疯了
but Lieutenant Dan, he was mad.
来吧!
Come on!
你这算是风暴吗?
You call this a storm?
来吧  你这狗娘养的!
Come on, you son of a bitch!
咱们来较量一下吧!
It's time for a show down!
你和我!
You and me!
我就在这儿  来捉我吧!
I'm right here! Come and get me!
你绝不能弄沉...
You'll never sink...
这条...
this...
船!
boat!
卡门飓风昨天过境
Hurricane Carmen came through here yesterday,
沿途几乎摧毁了一切
destroying nearly everything in its path.
沿海的其他城镇也一样
And as in other towns up and down the coast,
拉巴特湾的捕虾业
Bayou La Batre's entire shrimping industry
成为卡门飓风的最大受害者
has fallen victim to Carmen
渔港完全成了废墟
and has been left in utter ruin.
记者被告知
This reporter has learned,
实际上只有一条捕虾船
in fact, only one shrimping boat
幸免于难
actually survived the storm.
露西  露西  福雷斯来了
Louise. Louise, there's Forrest.
从此以后  捕虾就很容易了
After that, shrimping was easy.
将会有丰厚的回报
There will be great bounty
我的上帝...
Oh, my God...
因为人们仍然需要虾
Since people still needed them shrimps
来做虾串烧和虾烧烤什么的
for shrimp cocktails and barbecues and all
而我们的船是唯一剩下的了
and we were the only boat left standing,
他们只能来布巴·甘这里买虾
Bubba Gump shrimp's what they got.
我们购置了一大堆船
We got a whole bunch of boats.
有12条珍妮号  还有一个大仓库
12 Jennys, big old warehouse.
我们还订做了帽子  上面写着"布巴·甘"
We even have hats that say "Bubba Gump" on them.
布巴·甘捕虾公司
Bubba Gump Shrimp.
这名字家喻户晓
It's a household name.
等等  小兄弟
Hold on there, boy.
你是说你就是...
Are you telling me you're the owner
布巴·甘捕虾公司的老板?
of the Bubba Gump Shrimp Corporation?
对  我们挣了一大堆钱
Yes. We got more money than Davy Crockett.
孩子  我听过很多牛皮
Boy, I heard some whoppers in my time,
这是最大的一个
but that tops them all.
我们身边正坐着一个百万富翁
We were sitting next to a millionaire.
嗯  我觉得那是个很有趣的故事
Well, I thought it was a very lovely story,
你讲得真好
and you tell it so well,
非常热情洋溢
with such enthusiasm.
你想看看丹中尉长什么样吗?
Would you like to see what Lieutenant Dan looks like?
是的  我想看
Yes, I would.
这个就是他
That's him right there.
我再讲点关于丹中尉的事
Let me tell you something about Lieutenant Dan.
福雷斯...
Forrest...
我一直还没谢谢你救我一命
I never thanked you for saving my life.
他从来没说出来
He never actually said so,
但我想他跟上帝已经讲和了
but I think he made his peace with God.
这是17天里第二次
For the second time in 17 days,
福特总统幸免被刺杀
President Ford escaped possible assassination today.
总部呼叫珍妮一号  总部呼叫珍妮一号
Base to Jenny 1. Base to Jenny 1.
珍妮一号  请说
Jenny 1. Go, Margo.
有福雷斯的电话
Forrest has a phone call.
嗯  你跟他说他迟点再回电话
Yeah, well, you'll have to tell them to call him back.
他现在很忙
He is indisposed at the moment.
他妈妈病了
His mama's sick.
妈妈在哪儿?
Where's Mama?
她在楼上
She's upstairs.
嗨  福雷斯
Hi, Forrest.
明天见
I'll see you tomorrow.
好的
Oh, all right.
你的腿全好了  是吗  孩子?
Sure got you straightened out, didn't we, boy?
怎么了  妈妈?
What's the matter, Mama?
我快死了  福雷斯
I'm dying, Forrest.
进来  坐下
Come on in, sit down over here.
为什么你快死了  妈妈?
Why are you dying, Mama?
我的时候到了
It's my time.
因为我的时候到了
It's just my time.
现在...
Oh, now...
你不用害怕  宝贝
don't you be afraid, sweet heart.
死亡只是生命的一部分
Death is just a part of life.
是我们注定要面对的
Something we're all destined to do.
我并不知道
I didn't know it,
但我注定要做你的妈妈
but I was destined to be your mama.
我就尽力做好
I did the best I could.
你做得很好
You did good.
嗯...  我相信你能实现自己的命运
Well... I happen to believe you make your own destiny.
你要凭着上帝所给予的做到最好
You have to do the best with what God gave you.
我的命运是什么  妈妈?
What's my destiny, Mama?
你要自己去弄明白
You're going to have to figure that out for yourself.
人生就像一盒各式各样的巧克力
Life is a box of chocolates, Forrest.
你永远不知道下一块将会是哪种
You never know what you're going to get.
妈妈总有办法把事情说清楚
Mama always hada way of explaining things
让我也能听明白
so I could understand them.
我会想念你的  福雷斯
I will miss you, Forrest.
她得了癌症
She had got the cancer
在星期二去世了
and died on a Tuesday.
我给她买了顶新帽子
I bought her a new hat
上面有很多小花
with little flowers on it.
我要说的说是这么多了
And that's all I have to say about that.
你不是说你在等7路车吗?
Didn't you say you were waiting for the number 7 bus?
等一下还会有下一班车的
There'll be another one along shortly.
现在因为我成了足球明星和战争英雄
Now, because I had been a football star and war hero
以及全国知名的人物和捕虾船的船长
and national celebrity and a shrimping boat captain
以及大学毕业生
and a college graduate,
亚拉巴马州绿茵镇的父老乡亲
the city fathers of Greenbow, Alabama,
决定给我一个好工作
decided to get together and offered me a fine job.
所以我不再回去和丹中尉一起工作了
So I never went back to work for Lieutenant Dan,
但他继续打理着我们布巴·甘公司的财产
though he did take care of my Bubba Gump money.
他替我买了一家卖苹果的公司的股票
He got me invested in some kind of fruit company.
后有他打电话给我
So then I got a call from him
说我们再也不用担心没钱花了
saying we don't have to worry about money no more,
我说："好啊  又少一件麻烦事"
and I said, "That's good. One less thing."
我有了新的希望...
I've got a new hope...
妈妈说过财产不用太多
Now Mama said there's only so much fortune
一个人用不了多少
a man really needs,
多余的钱只是用来炫耀
and the rest is just for showing off.
所以我拿出一大堆
So I gave a whole bunch of it
给四方福音教堂...
to the Four square Gospel Church...
又拿出一大堆给拉巴特湾渔场医院...
and I gave a whole bunch to the Bayou La Batre Fishing Hospital...
虽然布巴已经死了
and even though Bubba was dead
丹中尉也说我是笨蛋
and Lieutenant Dan said I was nuts,
我还是把布巴那一份给了布巴的妈妈
I gave Bubba's mama Bubba's share.
你猜怎么着?
You know what?
她再也不用去任何人家的厨房干活了
She didn't have to work in nobody's kitchen no more.
那感觉真不错
That smells wonderful.
因为我成了亿万富翁
And 'cause I was a gozillionaire
并且我喜欢干活
and I liked doing it so much,
我免费帮他们割草
I cut that grass for free.
但到了晚上无事可干
But at night time when there was nothing to do
房子空空荡荡的
and the house was all empty,
我会经常想念珍妮
I'd always think of Jenny.
然后...  她就出现了
And then... she was there.
你好  福雷斯
Hello, Forrest.
你好  珍妮
Hello, Jenny.
珍妮回来与我一起住
Jenny came back and stayed with me.
也许因为她没什么别的地方可去了
Maybe it was because she had no where else to go,
也许因为她太累了
or maybe it was because she was so tired
因为她总是在睡觉
'cause she went to bed and slept and slept
好象她多年没睡觉了
like she hadn't slept in years.
有她在家真好
It was wonderful having her home.
每天我们都散步
Every day we'd take a walk,
我不停地跟她说话
and I'd jabber on like a monkey in a tree,
她听我说乒乓球和捕虾
and she'd listen about Ping-Ponging and shrimping
还有妈妈去天堂的事
and Mama making a trip up to heaven.
我不停地说
I did all the talking.
珍妮总是很安静
Jenny most of the time was real quiet.
你怎么能这么做?
How could you do this?
有时我想石头会不够用
Sometimes I guess there just aren't enough rocks.
我一直不知道她为什么回来
I never really knew why she came back,
但我不介意
but I didn't care.
就象昔日重来
It was like olden times.
我们又形影不离了
We was like peas and carrots again.
每天我都会采来好看的花
Every day, I'd pick pretty flowers
放在她的房间里
and put them in her room for her,
而她给了我人所能得到的最好的礼物
and she gave me the best gift anyone could ever get
在整个世界里
in the wide world.
这是最适合跑步的
They're made just for running.
带我回家见亲朋
Carry me home to see my kin
他还教我如何跳舞
And she even showed me how to dance.
我又想起老朋友
I miss ol'Bammy once again
我不再对他不起
And I think it's a sin
亚拉巴马我的家...
Sweet home Alabama...
我们就象一家人  珍妮和我...
Well, we was like family, Jenny and me...
那是我一生最快乐的时光
and it was the happiest time in my life.
你看还要看吗?
You done watching it?
我要去睡了
I'm going to bed.
你能嫁给我吗?
Will you marry me?
我会做个好丈夫的  珍妮
I'd make a good husband, Jenny.
你会的  福雷斯
You would, Forrest.
但你不能嫁给我
But you won't marry me.
你不愿意娶我的
You don't want to marry me.
你为什么不爱我  珍妮?
Why don't you love me, Jenny?
我不是很聪明
I'm not a smart man,
但我知道什么是爱
but I know what love is.
珍妮
Jenny.
福雷斯  我真的爱你
Forrest, I do love you.
那你为什么要跑?
Where are you running off to?
我没有跑
I'm not running.
那一天
That day,
不知什么原因
for no particular reason,
我决定出去跑一趟
I decided to go for a little run.
所以我跑到路的尽头
So I ran to the end of the road,
当我到达那里  我想也许我能跑到城边
and when I got there, I thought maybe I'd run to the end of town.
卡特总统因中暑病倒...
President Carter, suffering from heat exhaustion...
而当我到达那里
And when I got there,
我想也许我能跑遍绿茵县
I thought maybe I'd just run across Greenbow County.
这时我想既然我跑了那么远
Now, I figured since I'd run this far,
也许我可以跑遍亚拉巴马州
maybe I'd just run across the great state of Alabama.
我就这么做了
And that's what I did.
我横越整个亚拉巴马
I ran clear across Alabama.
不知什么原因  我继续跑
No particular reason. I just kept on going.
我一直跑到大海
I ran clear to the ocean.
当我到达那里
And when I got there,
我想既然我跑了那么远
I figured since I'd gone this far,
也许不如掉头继续跑
might as well turn around, just keep on going.
然后当我跑到另一个大海
And when I got to another ocean,
我想既然我跑了那么远
I figured since I'd gone this far.
我也许不如掉头
I might as well just turn back
继续跑下去
and keep right on going.
当我累了  我就睡觉
when I got tired, I slept.
当我饿了  我就吃饭
when I got hungry, I ate.
当我想去
When I had to go.
你知道
you know.
我就去
I went.
所以
And so.
你不停地跑?
you just ran?
对
Yeah.
看着路在车轮下延伸
Lookin' out at the road rushin' under my wheels
看着一年年时光飞逝
Lookin' back at the years gone by
就象一片片夏日农田
Like so many summer fields
六五年那时我十七岁
In '65, I was 17
我在一刻不停地奔跑
And runnin' up one on one
我不知道跑到了何处
I don't know where I'm runnin' now
我只是在不停地奔跑
I'm just runnin' on
奔跑
Runnin' on
无缘无故地奔跑
Runnin' on empty
奔跑
Runnin' on
精疲力竭
Runnin' dry
奔跑...
Runnin' on...
我想了很多事...
I'd think a lot...
关于妈妈和布巴还有丹中尉
about Mama and Bubba and Lieutenant Dan.
但最经常的
But most of all,
我在想念珍妮
I thought about Jenny.
我非常想念她
I thought about her a lot.
两年多来
For more than two years,
一位名叫福雷斯·甘的人
a man named Forrest Gump,
来自亚拉巴马绿茵县的园艺师  除了睡觉
a gardener from Greenbow, Alabama, stopping only to sleep,
就是不停跑步横越美国
has been running across America.
查尔斯·库珀为你报导
Charles Cooper brings you this report.
他这是第四次
For the fourth time
进行横越美国的旅程
on his journey across America,
福雷斯·甘  来自亚拉巴马绿茵县的园艺师
Forrest Gump, the gardener from Greenbow, Alabama,
今天将再次跑过密西西比河
is about to cross the Mississippi River again today.
天那  福雷斯?  先生  你为什么要跑?
I'll be damned. Forrest? Sir, where are you running?
你是为了世界和平吗?
Are you doing this for world peace?
你是为了无家可者吗?
Are you doing this for the homeless?
你是为了妇女权利吗?
Are you running for women's rights?
为了保护环境吗?
The environment?
他们就是不相信
they just couldn't believe
有些人跑步
that Somebody would do all that running
什么都不为
for no particular reason.
你为什么这样做?
Why are you doing this?
我只是想跑
I just felt like running.
I just felt like runnin'.
是你
That's you.
我不敢相信真的是你
I can't believe it's really you.
然后...  不知什么原因
Now... for some reason,
我所做的事好象
what I was doing seemed to...
在某些人看来有了意义
make sense to people.
我的头脑中好象响起一声警报
It was like an alarm went off in my head.
我说  "他是个实干家
I said, "Here's a guy that's got his act together.
他拥有所有问题的答案"
Here's somebody who has the answer."
我要追随你  甘先生
I'll follow you anywhere, Mr. Gump.
于是我有了伙伴
So I got company.
然后  我有了更多的伙伴
And after that, I got more company.
然后  又有更多的人加入
And then, even more people joined in.
有人后来告诉我
Somebody later told me
人们看到了希望
it gave people hope.
那时...
Now...
那时我什么也不知道
Now, I don't know anything about that,
有些人曾经问我
but some of those people asked me
我能不能帮助他们
if I could help them out.
我想你也许能够帮助我
I was wondering if you might help me.
我是做贴纸生意的
I'm in the bumper sticker business.
我需要一句好的口号
I need a good slogan,
你很有天才
and since you've been so inspirational,
我想你也许能帮助我...
I thought you might be able to help me...
啊!  你刚跑过...
Whoa, man! You just ran
一大堆狗屎!
through a big pile of dog shit!
不管它
It happens.
什么  狗屎?
What, shit?
有时
Sometimes.
几年后  我听说那个家伙
And some years later, I heard that that fella
想出来一条贴纸口号
did come up with a bumper sticker slogan
赚了一大笔钱
and made a lot of money off of it.
还有一次  我一个人跑着
Another time, I was running along.
遇到个卖T恤衫赔了本的人
Somebody who'd lost all his money in the T-shirt business,
他希望把我的脸印在T恤衫上
he wanted to put my face on a T-shirt,
但他不太会画画
but he couldn't draw that well,
他也没带照相机
and he didn't have a camera.
用这个吧  反正没人喜欢这颜色
Here, use this one. Nobody likes that color anyway.
祝你过得好
Have a nice day.
几年后  我听说
Someyears later, I found out
那个人确实想出了一个T恤图案
that that man did come up with an idea for a T-shirt.
赚了一大笔钱
He made a lot of money.
总之  就象我说过的
Anyway, like I was saying,
我有了很多伙伴
I had a lot of company.
我妈妈总是说
My mama always said,
"你得丢开以往的事
"You got to put the past behind you
"才能不断继续前进"
before you can move on."
我想那就是我这次跑步的意义了
And I think that's what my running was all about.
我跑了三年...
I had run for three years...
两个月...
two months...
14天又16小时
14 days, and 16 hours.
安静  安静  他有话要说
Quiet. Quiet. He's going to say something.
我很累了
I'm pretty tired.
现在我想回家了
Think I'll go home now.
那我们该怎么办?
Now what are we supposed to do?
就这样...
And just like that...
我跑步的日子结束了
my runnin' days was over.
我回到亚拉巴马的家
So I went home to Alabama.
不久前  下午2时25分
Moments ago, at 2:25 P.M.,
当里根总统走出...
as President Reagan was leaving the...
开了五至六枪
Five or six gunshots were fired
一个不知名的凶手
by an would-be assassin.
总统胸部中弹...
The president was shot in the chest...
我拿到邮件
I picked up the mail.
有一天  天气晴朗
And one day, out of the blue clear sky,
我收到一封珍妮的来信
I got a letter from Jenny
问我能不能来萨凡纳
wondering if I could come down to Savannah
来看她  所以我就来了
and see her, and that's what I'm doing here.
她在电视上看到我...  跑步
She saw me on TV... running.
我正要乘9路车去里奇蒙街
I'm supposed to go on the number 9 bus to Richmond Street
然后下车向左走
and get off and go one block left
到亨利街1947号...
to 1947 Henry Street...
4单元
apartment 4.
那你不必乘公交车
Why, you don't need to take a bus.
亨利街离这儿只有五六个街区...
Henry Street is just five or six blocks...
就往那边
down that way.
往那边?
Down that way?
往那边
Down that way.
很高兴和你聊天
It was nice talking to you.
我希望你一切顺利!
I hope everything works out for you!
福雷斯!
Forrest!
你好吗?
How you doin'?
进来  进来!
Come in! Come in!
我收到了你的信
I got your letter.
哦  我还正担心你收不到呢
Oh, I was wondering about that.
这是你住的地方?
This your house?
对  现在很乱
Yeah. It's messy right now.
我刚下班回来
I just got off work.
很好
It's nice.
你还买了空调
You got air-conditioning.
谢谢
Thank you.
我吃了
I ate some.
我  嗯...  保存了一本你的剪报和...
I, uh, kept... kept a scrap book of... of your clippings and...
别的东西  给你
everything. There you are.
对  我看见你跑了
Yes, I got you running.
我跑了很长的路
I ran a long way.
很长的时间
It's a long time.
那...
There...
听我说  福雷斯  我不知该怎么说
Listen, Forrest, I don't know how to say this.
我...
I just...
我想向你道歉
I want to apologize
为我对你做的一切  因为...
for anything that I ever did to you 'cause...
我做得很糟...
I was messed up...
一直以来  而且...
for a long time, and...
嗨  你好
Hey, you.
这位是我从亚拉巴马来的老朋友
This is my old friend from Alabama.
你好吗?
How do you do?
下星期我的日程安排要改了  所以我...
Next week my schedule changes, so I can...
没问题  我得走了  我没停车位
No problem. Got to go. I'm double-parked.
好吧  谢谢
O.K. Thanks.
这是我很好的朋友甘先生
This is my very good friend Mr. Gump.
你能问声好吗?
Can you say hi?
你好  甘先生
Hello, Mr. Gump.
你好
Hello.
我能去看电视吗?
Can I go watch TV now?
可以  但声音轻点
Yes. Just keep it low.
你做妈妈了  珍妮
You're a mama, Jenny.
我做妈妈了
I'm a mama.
他名字叫福雷斯
His name's Forrest.
和我一样!
Like me!
他的名字和他爸爸一样
I named him after his daddy.
他的爸爸也叫福雷斯?
He got a daddy named Forrest, too?
你就是他爸爸  福雷斯
You're his daddy, Forrest.
福雷斯  看着我
Forrest, look at me.
看着我  福雷斯
Look at me, Forrest.
你不用担心
There's nothing you need to do.
你没有做错事
You didn't do anything wrong.
好吗?
O. K?
他漂亮吗?
Isn't he beautiful?
他是我见过最漂亮的
He's the most beautiful thing I've ever seen.
可是...
But...
他...  他聪明吗?  比如他能不能...
is... is he s-smart? Like, can he...
他非常聪明
He's very smart.
他是他班上最聪明的一个
He's one of the smartest in his class.
没事的  去和他聊聊吧
Yeah, it's O.K. Go talk to him.
你在看什么?
What are you watching?
伯特和埃妮
Bert and Ernie.
福雷斯...
Forrest...
我生病了
I'm sick.
什么  你是不是感冒了
What, do you have a cough due to a cold?
我染上了一种病毒  医生...
I have some kind of virus, and the doctors,
他们不知道是什么病毒
they don't know what it is,
他们也不知道如何医治
and there isn't anything they can do about it.
你和我一起回家吧
You could come home with me.
珍妮  你和...
Jenny, you and...
小福雷斯
little Forrest
一起
could come stay
住到绿茵镇来
at my house in Greenbow.
要是你病了我会照顾你
I'll take care of you if you're sick.
你愿意娶我吗  福雷斯?
Would you marry me, Forrest?
好的
O.K.
请坐
Please take your seats.
福雷斯?
Forrest?
快开始了
It's time to start.
你的领带
Your tie.
丹中尉
Lieutenant Dan.
你好  福雷斯
Hello, Forrest.
你有双新腿了
You got new legs.
新腿!
New legs!
对  我有双新腿了
Yeah. I got new legs.
是定做的
Custom-made.
钛合金的
Titanium alloy.
航天飞机也是用它造的
It's what they use on the space shuttle.
魔腿
Magic legs.
这位...
This...
是我的未婚妻
is my fiancee.
苏珊
Susan.
丹中尉
Lieutenant Dan.
嗨  福雷斯
Hi, Forrest.
丹中尉...
Lieutenant Dan...
这位是我的珍妮
this is my Jenny.
很高兴能见到你
Hi. It's nice to meet you finally.
福雷斯  你愿意让珍妮
Do you, Forrest, take Jenny
做你的妻子吗?
to be your wife?
珍妮  你愿意让福雷斯
Do you, Jenny, take Forrest
做你的丈夫吗?
to be your husband?
那么我宣布你们结为夫妻
And so I pronounce you man and wife.
嘿  福雷斯...
Hey, Forrest...
你在越南害怕过吗?
were you scared in Vietnam?
是的
Yes.
我...
Well, I...
我不知道
I don't know.
当雨停的时候
Sometimes it would stop raining
有时能看到星星...
long enough for the stars to come out...
那感觉很好
and then it was nice.
就象太阳下山前
It was like just before the sun goes to bed
在拉巴特湾
down on the bayou.
海面的闪闪鳞光...
there was always a million sparkles on the water...
就象山间的湖水
like that mountain lake.
那样的清澈  珍妮
It was so clear, Jenny,
就象另一片天空
it looked like there were two skies
两重天空
one on top of the other.
还有在沙漠里  当太阳升起...
And then in the desert, when the sun comes up...
我分不清
I couldn't tell
哪儿是天  哪儿是地
where heaven stopped and the earth began.
真是美丽
It's so beautiful.
我但愿那时和你在一起
I wish I could've been there with you.
你确实在的
You were.
我爱你
I love you.
你在星期六清晨死去
You died on a Saturday morning.
我把你葬在我们的树下
And I had you placed here under our tree.
我把你父亲的房子
And I had that house of your father's
推成了平地
bulldozed to the ground.
妈妈
Mam
总是说...
always said
死亡是生命的一部分
that dyin' was a part of life.
我真的希望不是这样
I sure wish it wasn't.
小福雷斯...
Little Forrest is...
很好
doing just fine.
"不过..."
"But..."
就要去上学了
About to start school again so on,
还有...
and...
我给他做早餐,  午餐和晚餐
and I make his breakfast, lunch, and dinner
每天
every day.
我让他...
I make sure he...
梳头
combs his hair
让他每天刷牙
and brushes his teeth every day.
教他怎么打乒乓球
Teaching him how to play Ping-Pong.
他打得很棒
He's really good.
福雷斯  你来发球
Uh, Forrest, you go.
我们经常钓鱼
We fish a lot.
我们每天晚上读书
And every night, we read a book.
他聪明极了  珍妮
He's so smart, Jenny.
你一定会为他骄傲
You'd be so proud of him.
我会的
I am.
他还给你写了封信
He, uh, wrote you a... a letter.
他说不许我看  我不能看
And he says I can't read it. I'm not supposed to,
所以我把它放在这儿给你
so I'll just leave it here for you.
珍妮...
Jenny...
我不知道是妈妈对
I don't know if Mama was right
还是丹中尉对
or if it... it's Lieutenant Dan.
我不知道
I don't know...
是否我们每个人都有
if we each have a...
注定的命运...
destiny...
还是我们的生命中只有偶然
or if we're all just floating around accidental-like
象在风中飘...
on a breeze...
但我想...
but I... I think...
也许两者都有吧
maybe it's both.
也许两者都在同时发生着
Maybe both get happening at the same time.
可是我想念你  珍妮
But I miss you, Jenny.
如果你想要什么...
If there's anything you need...
我就在你身边
I won't be far away.
你的车来了
Here's your bus.
好吧
O.K.
嗨...
Hey...
我知道
I know this.
我会在故事会上讲故事
I'm gonna share that for show-and-tell
因为奶奶曾给你读过
because Grandma used to read it to you.
我最喜欢的书
My favorite book.
好了
Here we are.
你该走了
here you go.
嘿  福雷斯...
Hey, Forrest...
不要...
don't...
我想告诉你我爱你
I want to tell you I love you.
我也爱你  爸爸
I love you, too, Daddy.
我就在这儿等你回来
I'll be right here when you get back.
你知道这是校车  是吧?
You understand this is the bus to school, now, don't you?
当然  你是多萝西·哈里斯  我是福雷斯·甘
Of course, and you're Dorothy Harris, and I'm Forrest Gump.